<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ephesus vvarning before her woe A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse on Passion Sunday, the 17. of March last. By Sampson Price, Bachelour of Diuinity, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford: and lecturer at S. Olaus.</title>
            <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10076</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20330</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115214</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850433</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850433</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15635</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10076)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15635)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1555:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ephesus vvarning before her woe A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse on Passion Sunday, the 17. of March last. By Sampson Price, Bachelour of Diuinity, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford: and lecturer at S. Olaus.</title>
                  <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By G. Eld for Iohn Barnes, dwelling in Hosier lane, neere Holborne Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Variant: title page omits "and lecturer at S. Olaus".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15635:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15635:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>EPHESVS</hi> VVARNING BEFORE HER <hi>WOE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON <hi>Preached at Pauls Croſſe on Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Sunday, the 17. of March <hi>laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By SAMPSON PRICE, Bachelour of Diuinity, <hi>of</hi> Exeter <hi>Colledge in</hi> Oxford:</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by G. ELD for <hi>Iohn Barnes,</hi> dwelling in Hoſier lane, neere Holborne Condut 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15635:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15635:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable the <hi>Lord Viſcount Liſle, Lord Chamberlaine</hi> to the Queenes Maieſty, and Lord <hi>Gouernour of his Maieſties Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onary</hi> Towne of Vluſhing, <hi>Mercy and peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Speech of <hi>Salomon</hi> is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl. 12.12.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lc. Alex. l. <hi>1.</hi> ſtr. p. <hi>1.</hi> Hic ſcripto, ille vece praedicat. Animae ſunt ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Orationes. Id. ib. <hi>Mar. 12.41, 43.</hi> Cyp. Tr. de op. &amp; elcemoſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and muſt continue true: <hi>of making many books there is no end;</hi> while the <hi>world</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth, occaſion will not bee wanting of <hi>ſpeaking</hi> and <hi>writing.</hi> Our <hi>Church</hi> hath many deſeruing <hi>Labourers,</hi> who by <hi>voyce</hi> and <hi>pen</hi> ſeeke to build vp the walles of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> My deſire is to caſt my <hi>Mite</hi> into the <hi>Treaſury,</hi> as that poore <hi>widdow</hi> did, whom our <hi>Sauiour</hi> commended, not conſidering <hi>quantum, ſed ex quanto de diſſet;</hi> how much, but <hi>of how much</hi> ſhe offered: reſpecting rather the <hi>affection</hi> of the giuer, then the <hi>quantity</hi> of the guiſt. This <hi>Sermon</hi> (by the earnest ſollicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome religious <hi>hearers</hi> and my deare fauorers) was brought from the <hi>Croſſe</hi> to the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> and is now licenced to be a generall <hi>Remembrancer</hi> of all thoſe who ſhall <hi>read</hi> or <hi>heare</hi> it;<note place="margin">Spartian. in vita Adrian. Imp.</note> to whom I wiſh as happy a memory as that of <hi>Adrian,</hi> who perfectly
<pb facs="tcp:15635:3"/>(euer afterward) knew them that had but once ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto him.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> In Morall actions and ciuill affaires <hi>feare</hi> oftentimes hath hindred the memory of the wiſest; as it is recorded of <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> that hee was at a <hi>Nonplus</hi> beeing to ſpeake before <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon:</hi> and as it fell out to <hi>Theophra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> before the <hi>Areopagites</hi> of <hi>Athens.</hi> But a holy feare of Gods name, muſt bee the ground of our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance</hi> and <hi>Repentance.</hi> Your Honour hath obtained a bleſsed report for your <hi>Noble Vertues,</hi> and imitation of your Heroicall <hi>Brother.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir Phil. Sidney.</note> I haue therefore aduentured to dedicate this poore <hi>labour</hi> vnto your <hi>protection,</hi> to lodge ſafely from the <hi>ſnarling of biting cenſurers,</hi> as vnder the couert of <hi>Minerua's</hi> ſhield. Your <hi>honorable</hi> countenance ſo <hi>lately</hi> and <hi>cheerefully</hi> ready to call me (from this ſtipend which I enioy amongſt many louing and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy friends) to a more ample maintenance (though God diſpoſed otherwiſe of it) hath obliged mee to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <hi>by that little cunning</hi> which my right hand hath;<note place="margin">S. Olau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Southwarke.</note> ſo great a <hi>Kindnes.</hi> I can ſeale my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes by no better a <hi>teſtimony</hi> then this;<note place="margin">Pſ. 137.5.</note> crauing ſtill the <hi>continuance</hi> of your honorable <hi>fauour. God</hi> the great rewarder continue his <hi>bleſſings</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you and your <hi>Honorable Lady</hi> and hopefull <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and at the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of the Iuſt, crowne hee you all with euerlaſting <hi>glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in all duty. SAMPSON PRICE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15635:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>EPHESVS WARNING</hi> before her Woe.</head>
            <head type="sub">Lord Ieſus begin and end.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVE. 2.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and doe the firſt workes, or elſe I will come vnto thee quickly, and will remoue thy Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſticke out of his place, except thou repent.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the <hi>ſinne of the old World</hi> did multiply and grew a burthen to the Earth: the Sonnes of God taking them wiues, of all which they choſe, whether <hi>Virgins or married vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.;</hi> the moſt of them being Gyants,<note place="margin">Mercerus &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unius in Gen.</note> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſtature, but in cruell conditions, according to <hi>Philo</hi> and <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> infamous for their tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ouer others, bringing them in ſubiection, and eating their fleſh;<note place="margin">Theod. q. <hi>84.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Gen.</note> euery imagination of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15635:4"/>thoughts of their hearts onely euill continually. <hi>It repented the Lord that he had made man on the Earth. Gen.</hi> 6.6. It is <hi>Verbum noſtra paruitati ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodatum,</hi> a word applied to our weaknes,<note place="margin">Chryſ. ho. <hi>22.</hi> in Gen.</note> to expreſſe the greatnes of their ſinnes, <hi>Quae miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordem Deum indignari fecerunt,</hi> which compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the mercifull God to be angry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non perturbatio ſed iudicium quo irrogatur poena,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. li. <hi>15.</hi> de ciu. c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Auſtin,</hi> It is no <hi>perturbation</hi> in God, but an impoſition of puniſhment.<note place="margin">Rup. l <hi>4.</hi> in Gen.</note> 
               <hi>Rupertus</hi> calleth it an <hi>argument</hi> of his pittie, ſhewing that he is loth to puniſh.</p>
            <p>Sixe ages he did forbeare them, a thouſand yeares and more, and gaue them <hi>Noah</hi> to preach repentance 120. yeares, before hee purged that <hi>Augaeum ſtabulum</hi> with a deluge of waters. The Sinnes of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> were exceeding great,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.24.</note> before fire and brimſtone were rayned downe by the hand of Chriſt from <hi>Iehouah</hi> his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as <hi>Marcus Arethuſius</hi> in the Syrinian Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell doth interpret that place,<note place="margin">Syrinienſ. conc. c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> againſt the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Photinus,</hi> that held Chriſt not to haue bene before his Mother. His <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>wrath</hi> is neuer full mixt with red Wine,<note place="margin">Pſal. 74.8.</note> to poure out the ſame with the dreggs thereof, till the meaſure of our <hi>Crimſon</hi> and <hi>Scarlet</hi> ſinnes be filled in. He ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>Watchmen</hi> to blowe the Trumpet and warne the people; but if they take not warning, <hi>their blood ſhall be vpon their owne heads. Ez.</hi> 33.4 If the <hi>Rod of his mouth,</hi> and Breath of his lips (ſo the word is called <hi>Iſ.</hi> 11.4.) cannot preuaile,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15635:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>hee taketh away this Candleſticke. And when once a Church ſhal looſe <hi>Prophets</hi> which are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to teach, <hi>Seers</hi> to foretell,<note place="margin">Ge. 20 7. 1 Sa. 9 9. 2 Pet. 1.13. 1 Cor 3.9. Lu. 12.42. Ez. 47.10.</note> 
               <hi>Remembrancers</hi> to put in mind, <hi>Huſbandmen</hi> to plow vp, <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> to diſtribute, <hi>Fiſhers</hi> to catch men, <hi>Starres</hi> to giue light, and <hi>Shepheards</hi> to feed, all bleſſings depart and curſes follow. Yet now it is threatned to <hi>Epheſus. Remember.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was truely acknowledged by <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus,</hi> that <hi>Bona eſt ars terrere ne peccemus:</hi> It is a good art which terrifieth from ſinning: yet as <hi>Auſt.</hi> fatherlike,<note place="margin">Aug. Ep. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si terrerentur et non docerentur improba quafi dominatio videretur,</hi> If thoſe that erre ſhould be terrified onely, and not be taught, it might ſeeme a kind of tyrannie: <hi>Sed rurſus ſi do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerentur et non terrerentur, vetuſtate conſuetudinis obdurarentur,</hi> But againe, if they ſhould be taught and not terrified, cuſtome would harden them, and make them pace but ſlowly to the way of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. Therefore S. <hi>Iohn, Legatus a latere,</hi> The Ambaſſadour who leaned on his Lords breaſt, partly by inſtruction, and partly by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, ſeeketh to win theſe <hi>collapſed Churches,</hi> whoſe <hi>reprehenſion</hi> may ſtirre vs vp to hearken, whoſe <hi>threats</hi> may make vs feare, whoſe <hi>fallings</hi> may make vs ſtand. Our ſinnes are as theirs, wee haue the <hi>luke-warmenes</hi> of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> which in this place I once propoſed as a warning.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 3.16.</note> Adde to this the little ſtrength of <hi>Philadelphia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 8.</note> Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of works with <hi>Sardis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> ſearching the depths of <hi>Sathan</hi> with <hi>Thyatira: Nicholaitans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 24.</note> as in <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamos</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15635:5"/>which held fornication to be no ſinne: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profeſſing to be Iewes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 14.</note> as in <hi>Smyrna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 9.</note> (Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans amongſt vs) but are the Synagogue of <hi>Sathan:</hi> with <hi>Epheſus</hi> wee haue left our <hi>firſt</hi> loue, of which I am come to put you in remembrance by this Text. The Lord make it as profitable as it is vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. <hi>Remember.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Author</hi> of which words is one who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto <hi>Iohn</hi> like the Sonne of man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> like vnto a man, cloathed with a <hi>Garment</hi> downe to the foote, ſignifying his <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> and <hi>Principality: Girt</hi> about the paps with a <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den girdle,</hi> ſignifying his care euer to be ready for his Church: his <hi>head and hayres</hi> white as wool and ſnow, ſignifying his eternitie: his <hi>Eyes</hi> as a flame of fire, ſignifying his quicke ſight peircing to the very thoughts: his <hi>Feete</hi> like vnto fine braſſe ſignifying his ability to encounter againſt <hi>Sinne, Sathan</hi> and <hi>Death.</hi> His <hi>voyce</hi> as the ſound of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waters, ſignifying the greatnes and power of it. The 7. <hi>Starres</hi> in his right hand are the ſeauen <hi>Pastors</hi> of the Churches in Aſia, called <hi>Angels, vt dignitatem ſeruent in nomine quam explent in operatione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. in Mat.</note> that they might retaine that dignity in name, whereunto by office they are entituled. Not ſome <hi>Biſhops</hi> onely, as <hi>Alcaſar</hi> the leſuit in his new painted bul ke would haue it,<note place="margin">Arcan. ſenſ. in Apoc.</note> or the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple apart are aimed at, as <hi>Per erius</hi> thinketh, but more truely according to Saint <hi>Ambroſe, Haimo,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bede,</hi> both are to be ioyned, Paſtors &amp; people. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> was now (as our Sauiour) at this time led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15635:5"/>to the wildernes, where being diſabled to preach becauſe hee was an exile, like <hi>Zachary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr.</note> 
               <hi>cum lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui non potuit ſcripſit,</hi> when hee could not ſpeake, hee wrote; that the <hi>pen</hi> might make ſupply of the want of his tongue, eſpecially hauing his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from him who is <hi>the first and the last,</hi> from him who was dead and is aliue, and hath the keyes of death and of hell. He that runneth by may read his writing, bringing backe <hi>Epheſus</hi> to her principles. <hi>Remember.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Text</hi> as neceſſary for our times,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 5.16.</note> as our times are neere vnto <hi>Epheſus</hi> backſliding: wee may complaine as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> the <hi>daies</hi> are euill. The <hi>ſound</hi> of the word hath gone into all our land, the bright <hi>beames</hi> of the Goſpell haue gloriouſly ſhined vpon vs, the <hi>Bels</hi> of <hi>Aaron</hi> haue been long rung amongſt vs, yet we are like thoſe whom S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> taxed calling them <hi>Dormitantes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Au. l. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi> de doct. Chr.</note> halfe waking, neither altogether aſleepe in ignorance, nor throughly awaked to ſee ſo much of the truth as wee may. We haue many <hi>Profeſſors</hi> in mouth, <hi>Atheiſts</hi> in life, <hi>Protestants</hi> in appearance, <hi>Papiſts</hi> in heart, <hi>zealous</hi> in ſnew, nothing in deed. <hi>Others</hi> halt betwixt two opinions, and ſo fall from drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines to ſleepe, from ſlacknes to defection, from indifference to ſenſleſnes, and ſo to a loathing of all religion. The greateſt part haue forſaken their firſt loue. But heere is a ſcripture aiming at theſe and all other ſinnes, be they of neuer ſo tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent an eleuation. At thoſe <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> which like Wolues rauen the prey to ſhed blood, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15635:6"/>to deſtroy ſoules to get diſhoneſt gaine,<note place="margin">Ez. 22.27.18.</note> that though a mans cauſe be neuer ſo light in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of <hi>equity,</hi> it is not materiall if hee can make it vp in <hi>gold.</hi> At thoſe <hi>Prophets</hi> which daube with <hi>vntempered morter,</hi> ſeeing vanity and yet diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lyes, promiſing peace vnto the wicked and neuer ſpeak of wrath. At the idle <hi>Lozzel,</hi> who had rather <hi>beg</hi> &amp; ſteale then labour with his hands. At the <hi>edge</hi> of priuate <hi>reuenge</hi> which will haue eye for eye, hand for hand, ſatisfaction for any wrong. At the <hi>ſoaring</hi> Pride of Ambition, flying ſo high out of compaſſe that it flyeth it ſelfe out of breath, crying ſtill <hi>aut Caeſar aut nihil,</hi> as good to bee laſt as not firſt.<note place="margin">Mic. 6.10 11.12.</note> At the <hi>treaſures</hi> of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe in the houſes of the wicked. At the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable <hi>ſcant meaſure, bagge of deceitfull weights,</hi> and violent tongues. <hi>Mic.</hi> 6. At thoſe who haue erred through <hi>Wine</hi> and ſtrong drinke, whoſe bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is their God. At thoſe <hi>Tables</hi> which are full of <hi>vomit and filthines:</hi> though they heare precept vpon precept, line vpon line, they will goe and fall backward and be broken, and ſnared &amp; taken making a couenant with death, and an agreement with hel.<note place="margin">Ie. 48.11.</note> At thoſe who like <hi>Moab</hi> haue been at eaſe from their youth, and are ſetled vpon the lees of their ſinnes, their ſent neuer changed, <hi>Ie.</hi> 48. That I ſay to theſe, I ſay to all who haue forſaken their firſt loue, <hi>Remember.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As a tender-hearted <hi>Surgeon</hi> comming to his ſicke Patient for the cutting off a ioynt, ſeeing him feare and tremble, handleth it with much
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15635:6"/>care and compaſſion, and ſuddenly ſtriketh the ſtroake: ſo ſaith <hi>Gregory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gr. ho. <hi>11.</hi> in Ez.</note> dealeth <hi>Chriſt</hi> with his Church, his beloued Spouſe <hi>Epheſus. Saluberri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum temperamentum miſcens laudationem cum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptione. Rupertus</hi> calleth it a wholſome mixture where is commendation and reproofe. Both are met in this Epiſtle: where the <hi>Angell,</hi> that is the <hi>Paſtor</hi> of <hi>Epheſus: Timothy</hi> as <hi>Aureolus</hi> would haue it: or <hi>Oneſimus</hi> as ſome: or <hi>Tychicus</hi> as others and vnder him whole <hi>Epheſus</hi> is taxed for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſnes: the matter being thus debated. <hi>Epheſus thinke not but that I know thy workes: Thou maiſt deceiue the world, thou canſt not deceiue me.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Soloculis hominem, quibus aſpicit omnia, cernit.<note place="margin">Guid. metam.</note>
            </q>
            <p>This Sunne of righteouſnes, whoſe eyes are ten thouſand times brighter then the Sun, can pierce through the cloud of mens actions if it were darker then hell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know thy labour</hi> and it pleaſeth me. He was worthy of double honour. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17. <hi>I pitty thy patience:</hi> This <hi>Angell</hi> was not like <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> who at the mocking of the people <hi>curſed</hi> the day wherein he was born, and the man who brought tidings to his father that a manchild was born vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, not ſlaying him from the womb, wiſhing that his mother might haue been his graue, and her wombe alwayes to be great with him:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ie</hi> 48.14.15.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>Ie.</hi> 48.18. or like <hi>Ionas,</hi> who though he was ſchooled in the Whales belly, yet when all things went not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15635:7"/>according to his mind in the deſtruction of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niueh,<note place="margin">Ion. 4.9.</note> he became exceeding diſcontent, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended his vnlawful anger. He poſſeſſed his ſoule in patience,<note place="margin">Paetientia ipſum anat que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> portat Gr. in Ezech. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> becauſe hee loued them whom hee ſpake vnto. I commend thy <hi>diſcipline,</hi> how thou canſt not beare them which are cuill. Theſe and the like were the firſt fruits of thy affection, but alas thou haſt fallen off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe: yet I wil not the death of a ſinner, I rather wiſh thy conuerſion. <hi>Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in text. <hi>Gen. 3.9.</hi> Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. l. de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe. c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> They are like the words of God vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> when he called and ſaid vnto him, <hi>where art thou? De quibus bonis, de qua beatitudine, de qua gratia, in quam miſeriam cecidiſti?</hi> From how many good things bleſſings and graces, into what miſery haſt thou fallen? <hi>Non tam interrogatio, quam increpatio eſt,</hi> it was not ſo much an interrogation, as an increpation. Sometimes God vſeth to ſpeake by his ſecret <hi>inſpiration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kin. 20.4.</note> as to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 2 Ki. 2. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by his <hi>Angells,</hi> who ſpeake by <hi>voyce</hi> onely as to <hi>Chriſt, there came a voyce from heauen Ioh.</hi> 12. or by <hi>viſion internall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.28 Ge. 28.12. Ge. 18.1.4.</note> as the ladder that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaw in his dreame. <hi>Ge.</hi> 28. <hi>externall,</hi> in humane ſhape as to <hi>Abraham. Ge.</hi> 18. By other Creatures either <hi>without ſenſe,</hi> as by fire in the buſh to <hi>Moſes;</hi> or hauing ſenſe, as the <hi>Angell</hi> ſpake in <hi>Balaams Aſſe.</hi> Here becauſe writing remaineth when the voice periſeth, an Epiſtle is ſent vnto <hi>Epheſus</hi> teaching the art of the happieſt memory, whoſe obiects are good things once practiſed, omitted, &amp; euill things committed. <hi>Repentance</hi> muſt follow, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15635:7"/>doing the firſt workes, <hi>Repent and doe the firſt workes:</hi> A <hi>Spirit</hi> of ſlumber was fallen vpon <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> as heauy as that of <hi>Adam</hi> when he loſt his rib, or of <hi>Iſboſheth</hi> when hee loſt his head. The caſe ſtood betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Epheſus,</hi> as betwixt a louing ſonne and his ſicke father, who labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with a lethargie, The <hi>Phiſitian</hi> tels the ſon, that his fathers immoderate deſire of ſleepe is mortall, therefore hee muſt nor ſuffer him to ſlumber. The ſonne ſeeing his father heauy, <hi>pulſat, vellicat, pietate moleſtus eſt,</hi> hee knocketh, pulleth, and ſo ſeemes to be troubleſome, but it is becauſe hee loueth him.<note place="margin">Aug. ho. <hi>11.</hi> quinque hom. &amp; ſer. <hi>60.</hi> do verbis Domini inter ſe comp.</note> 
               <hi>AEgrotat humanum genus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin,</hi> All Mankind is ſicke of ſinne: amongſt theſe <hi>Epheſus. Christ Ieſus</hi> the great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition cryeth out <hi>Awake</hi> thou that ſleepeſt, open thine eyes, that thou ſleepe not in death, it is now time to ariſe, and repent, and doe the firſt workes. Either the <hi>Paſtors</hi> ſeeing their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching take little effect grew negligent, as <hi>Hugo Cardinalis</hi> ſuppoſeth the fault: or they were not ſo liberall to the poore, ſaith <hi>Arethas:</hi> or wee may vnderſtand it with <hi>Rich. de S. Victore</hi> of all faults now to be amended, for <hi>Chriſt</hi> will beare no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, hee is impatient of any further delayes, and therefore threateneth, <hi>or elſe I will come vnto thee quickly.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The Originall is, <hi>I will come to thee ſhortly,</hi> ſo the vulgar Latine giueth it to this ſenſe, <hi>Venio tibi,</hi> words taken in good part. His going forth is prepared as the morning and hee ſhall come vnto vs as the raine, as the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15635:8"/>latter and former raine vnto the earth, <hi>Oſ.</hi> 6. ſo <hi>Zac.</hi> 9. <hi>Reioyce greatly</hi> O <hi>daughter of Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6.3. Zac. 9.9.</note> 
               <hi>ſhout O daughter of Ieruſalem. Behold thy King commeth vnto thee.</hi> But heere it ſignifieth a iudgement, and therefore is rendred by <hi>Beza</hi> in theſe wordes, <hi>veniam aduerſum te cito,</hi> I will come againſt thee quickly: and his comming is for reuenge, <hi>And will remoue thy Candleſtick out of his place.</hi> The Church ſhall neuer be vtterly deſtroyed, but for ſinne the Goſpell is often remoued: <hi>Merito pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tietur vltorem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de verb. Dom. ſe. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>qui noluit audire praeceptorem.</hi> If men will not heare Gods precepts, they muſt beare his puniſhments. Thus loue is violent, and <hi>Foelix illa neceſsitas quae ad meltora compellit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Ep. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> it is a bleſſed neceſſity which enforceth vs to vertue. God who forbeareth a long time payeth home at the laſt, by remouing his Church: and vpon this, the taking away of the Miniſtry of the Goſpell and the profeſſion thereof, in ſtead of truth there muſt ſucceed Ignorance, Apoſtacie and Hereſie, vnleſſe repentance and the fruits thereof attend the preaching of the word. <hi>Remember therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee the drift of our wronged Sauiour: the <hi>ſum</hi> of the whole is a <hi>remembrance</hi> vnto <hi>Epheſus</hi> of a decay in ſpirituall graces, which muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, elſe the meanes of ſaluation ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from them. Wee may call it a ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>remedie</hi> againſt the fearefull ſinne of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie, or a heauenly <hi>qualification</hi> of Lawe and Goſpell, mercie and iudgment, or a diuine <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer</hi> of al Churches by <hi>Epheſus</hi> Preacher,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15635:80"/>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> an Euangeliſt, Apoſtle and Prophet, whoſe words which I haue read, without racking, fall a ſunder into two parts
<list>
                  <item>1. A remarkeable meditation for <hi>Epheſus, Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, &amp; repent, and doe the firſt workes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A zealous indignation vpon the not practiſing of this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Or elſe I will come vnto thee quickly, and will remoue thy can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alesticke out of his place, except thou repent.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The 1. generall part containeth 2. particular circumſtances.
<list>
                  <item>1. A recollection of time paſt, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member therefore from whence thou art fallen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A Chriſtian reſurrection for the time to come, <hi>And repent and doe the firſt workes.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The 2 pointeth out 2. other.
<list>
                  <item>1. A ſpeedy viſitation, <hi>Or elſe I will come vnto thee quickly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A terible execution of this com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mination, yet mixed with much compaſſion, <hi>And will remoue thy Candleſtick out of his place, except thou repent.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt includeth an <hi>accuſation</hi> of falling, deliuered to the memorie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15635:9"/>
The ſecond, an <hi>inquiſition</hi> of the former works to keepe from a final Apoſtaſie.</p>
            <p>The third, a ſudden <hi>triall,</hi> wherein without repentance there muſt be ſeuerity.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt, the downefall of Religion, and pietie. <hi>Remember.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Right Honorable, Right Worſhipfull, and bleſſed Brethren, I haue brought you a Text, wherein there is not onely <hi>Iohn, a Sonne of Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 3 17. Act. 4.36. Re. 2.7 If. 51.17.</note> but <hi>Barnabas, a Sonne of conſolation. Hee that hath an eare let him heare what the Spirit ſaith,</hi> or rather ſoundeth out, for there can be no man, vnleſſe he haue drunke the dregges of the <hi>Cup of ſlumber,</hi> but this meſſage muſt awake him. The Temple is opened, the liſts and land-markes of this <hi>holy Land</hi> propounded, and now come far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be ſurueied. Let me beſeech your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and cherefull attention: My onely aime ſhall be the glory of God, ſeruice of the Church, diſcharge of my Conſcience, and your inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion. The ſolemnity of the time and place requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a <hi>Paſſion-Text. Repentance</hi> is the <hi>Paſsion.</hi> The Lord grant that it may finde and leaue vs true practiſers of it. But I muſt remember to goe backe to the <hi>dore</hi> of my Text, the <hi>front</hi> and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head whereof is <hi>Remembrance,</hi> the 1. <hi>particular</hi> of my 1. <hi>generall. Remember therfore from whence thou art fallen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt all the <hi>faculties</hi> of the ſoule, there is none which ſooner waxeth old then <hi>memorie.</hi> Sins obliquitie hath cauſed the appetite ſtill to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15635:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſire, yet neuer to be ſatisfied, the <hi>affections</hi> to denie obedience vnto <hi>reaſon,</hi> the deſire to ſwell infinite, the will is often mad, the minde lame, the memorie of the beſt by nature forgetfull, and therefore <hi>grace</hi> muſt teach vs the <hi>art of memorie.</hi> Man forgetteth himſelfe to be man: wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the conquering <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierom.</note> amidſt their greateſt pompe and triumphs, had euer one at the backe of the Chariot to pull the Conqueror by the ſleeue, and ſo oft as the people ſhouted, to crye to him againe, <hi>Memento te hominem eſſe, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thou art a man.</hi> A leſſon which <hi>Simonides,</hi> the firſt humane inuentour of the art of <hi>memorie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tully.</note> taught <hi>Pauſanias</hi> King of the Lacedemonians at a banquet, being deſired to ſpeake ſomething of greateſt importance, which for the preſent was taken ſcornfully, but afterwards in a famine, the King confeſſed the wiſdome of the heathen man. It was the morning voice of <hi>Philips</hi> boy. <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Butler forgat <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 40.23 Gen. 41.51. Da. 2.8. Mat. 16.5. <hi>Sab. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Pli li.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ola ter. l.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> forgat all his toyle, and all his <hi>Fathers houſe. Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> dreamed, <hi>but the thing went from him,</hi> hee forgat his owne dreame. The Diſciples for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got <hi>to take bread with them. Meſſala Coruinus</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter a ſicknes forgot his <hi>owne name.</hi> Another men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned by <hi>Plinv,</hi> hauing a great fall,<note place="margin">Zuing. Theat.</note> forgot his <hi>owne Mother, Gregorius Trapezuntius</hi> in his old age the Greeke tongue, wherein he had excelled. <hi>Theſeus</hi> the white ſayle which his father charged him to ſet vp if he returned a victor into Crete, and vſing a blacke one it was diſmall to <hi>Agetus.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15635:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Orbilius</hi> forgot his Alphabet. <hi>Caluiſius</hi> the names of thoſe with whom hee conuerſed daily. <hi>Curio</hi> the Iudge forgot the cauſe he ſhould haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen iudgement vppon. <hi>Atticus,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Sophiſta,</hi> the names of the 4. Elements. The <hi>Thracians</hi> their Arithmeticke, ſo that they could not count aboue the number of 4. <hi>Epheſus</hi> here forgat her firſt workes, her firſt loue, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is rouſed vp. <hi>Memorie</hi> is the <hi>Diarie, Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides, and looking glaſse of a Chriſtian:</hi> It belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to thinges paſt, as <hi>Senſe</hi> doth to things pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent, and <hi>Hope</hi> to thinges future. <hi>Tully</hi> called it the print or trace of things. <hi>Quintilian,</hi> the ground of all learning. <hi>Plato,</hi> the mother of the <hi>Muſes. Aristotle,</hi> the <hi>Scribe</hi> of the Soule. The <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> the <hi>Lawyer,</hi> the <hi>Mathematician,</hi> the <hi>Merchant</hi> holds his booke of accounts, or remembrancer to be his <hi>canticum canticorum,</hi> the moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table booke that he hath. <hi>Many</hi> haue bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded for ſtrange memories. <hi>Portius Latro,</hi> who neuer needed to read any thing which he had once written. <hi>Aeltus Adrianus</hi> remembred the names and acts of all his Soldiers. <hi>Carmides</hi> of Greece, any thing which he had heard. <hi>Mythry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> was able to ſpeake 22. languages. <hi>Caeſar</hi> a Roman Dictator was able to write, ſpeake, and heare others diſcourſe at one and the ſame time. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> of <hi>Roterodame</hi> had a memory like a Net. Bleſſed <hi>Iewell,</hi> vſually began not to commit his Sermons to heart till the ringing of the Bell.<note place="margin">In vita eius.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is a ſingular gift of God, an extraordinarie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15635:10"/>perfection of art; which made <hi>Pythagoras</hi> beg memory of <hi>Mercury,</hi> being commanded to aske what hee would, except immortality, and hee ſhould haue it. But according to the <hi>obiect</hi> it is more commendable. There is <hi>Memoria vitanda,</hi> The remembrance of iniuries, ſeeking reuenge, as <hi>Iuno</hi> neuer left her <hi>Troian</hi> enemy but by Sea and land perſecuted him, which made him expoſtular
<q>Tantaene animis coeleſtibus irae.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Better it were for ſuch to haue,<note place="margin">Virg.</note> as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> wiſhed, the art of forgetfulneſſe rather then the art of this memory. You know how it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded in <hi>Caine, Eſau, Abſolon, Haman.</hi> There is <hi>memoria timenda,</hi> Gods remembrance of our ſinnes, in regard whereof <hi>Dauid</hi> prayed, Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not the ſins of my youth nor my tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Pſal. 25. So in our Lyturgy, Remember not Lord our offences,<note place="margin">Pſal 25.7.</note> nor the offences of our fore-Fathers, that is, to puniſh them in vs. There is <hi>Memoria petenda,</hi> the remembrance of vs in mercy, <hi>Dauids</hi> appeale, Lord remember <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> and all his afflictions. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132. and the <hi>good Theefe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 132 1.</note> Lord remember mee when thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt into thy kingdome. <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.<note place="margin">Luk 23.42.</note> There is <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria tenend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, A remembrance of God,</hi> I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the Lord. <hi>Ion.</hi> 2. <hi>Of his name,</hi> I haue remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred thy name O Lord in the night,<note place="margin">ion. 2.7.</note> and haue kept thy law. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. We muſt remember his maruellous workes that hee hath done,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.55.</note> 
               <hi>his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers and the iudgements of his mouth. Pſal.</hi> 105.<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.5.</note> Wee muſt remember his <hi>Sabaoth,</hi> Remember the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15635:116"/>Sabaoth day to keepe it holy, <hi>Exo.</hi> 20. Not that wee ſhould remember God <hi>but one day in ſeauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 20.8.</note> but that if we would be forgetfull, yet we ſhould remember him <hi>one day in ſeauen at the leaſt.</hi> We muſt remember <hi>Chriſts paſsion:</hi> to this end we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Euchariſt: This doe in remembrance of mee. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. We muſt remember <hi>death, iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.19.</note> 
               <hi>and hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt remember <hi>our Parents.</hi> Remember that thou waſt begot of them, and how canſt thou recompence them the things that they haue done for thee? <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7. <hi>Our paſtors,</hi> Remember them which haue the rule ouer you,<note place="margin">Ecc. 7.28.</note> who haue ſpoken vnto you the word of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. And here <hi>our falls</hi> appeare to be remembred,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.7.</note> by <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Remember therefore from whence thou art fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len:</hi> whence iſſueth this doctrinall obſeruation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is the duty of thoſe who haue fallen from any grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>to looke back vpon their former eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord himſelfe is a witneſſe to the truth of this point. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes, conſider your wayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hagg. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. A <hi>Method</hi> which the Prophet <hi>Zephanie</hi> vſed vnto the Iewes: for hauing rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them for their notable crimes,<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>Idolatry, fraud and cruelty, turning back from the Lord,</hi> beeing cloathed with ſtrange apparrell, and ſetled on their lees, <hi>then threatning</hi> the cutting downe of their Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, <hi>that</hi> their goods ſhould become a booty, and their houſes a deſolation, <hi>that</hi> the mighty man ſhould cry bitterly, <hi>that</hi> their blood ſhould be poured out as duſt, and their fleſh as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15635:11"/>the dung, <hi>that</hi> neither their ſiluer nor gold ſhould be able to deliuer them, <hi>he exhorteth</hi> them to conſider their eſtates.<note place="margin">Zeph. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Gather our ſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> yea gather together O Nation not deſired. Repentance will make a man gather himſelfe and all his wits together, which afore were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed and wandred vp and downe in vanity. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutite vos, Iunius</hi> tranſlateth it, ſearch, trye, fanne your ſelues. This courſe the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> took, I thought on my wayes, and turned my feet vnto thy teſtimonies. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. This was the practiſe of <hi>Peters repentance:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.59.</note> howſoeuer hee followed his Maiſter a farre off, yet hee came into the high Prieſts houſe, and ſate downe when they had kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled a fire in the midſt of the Hall: Better it had been for him to haue been without, freezing, then to ſtand by the fire with ſo many infectious lep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <hi>It was a cold night that took away his heat of loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No doubt hee heard many hard paſſages vpon his Maiſter, one boaſting that he had caſt downe the <hi>Nazarite,</hi> another that hee had tumbled him in <hi>Cedron,</hi> another that he had giuen a <hi>blow. Peter</hi> is ſilent, whatſoeuer they ſay, and <hi>Vno eodemque ſilentio firmat errorem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fulg. de myſter. Mediat. ad Thraſ. Vandal. Regem.</note> 
               <hi>qui loquendo non aſtruit ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem.</hi> When a man doth not ſeeke to confirme the truth by ſpeaking, his ſilence eſtabliſheth er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror: perhaps his ſilence betrayed him: But a maid beheld him and earneſtly looking vpon him ſaid, This man was alſo with him: which words were as the ſtone of little <hi>Dauid</hi> vnto that great Gyant <hi>Goliah.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15635:12"/>
Dux Foemina facti.</q>
            <p>The Woman began in Paradiſe: no maruell ſhe was in Court. <hi>Aut amat aut odit, nihil eſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium:</hi> There is no loue ſtronger then the loue of a woman.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 8.6.</note> 
               <hi>It is ſtrong as death:</hi> and no wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe like the wickednes of a wicked Woman. It abateth the courage,<note place="margin">Ec. 25.13.23.</note> maketh a heauy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and a wounded heart. Wine and Women will make Men of vnderſtanding to fall away. <hi>Eccl.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 19.2. Luk. 22.57.</note> 19. <hi>Peter denyed him ſaying,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Lu.</hi> 22. I know him not. <hi>Hee</hi> knew him not who called him and his brother from their old nets, who healed his wiues mother, who was transfigured before him on the mount. <hi>Hee</hi> had firſt of all the reſt confeſſed him to bee <hi>conſubſtantiall</hi> with the father. <hi>Hee</hi> had promiſed to liue and dye with him,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.33.</note> yet <hi>hee</hi> denyed him three ſeuerall times. <hi>Hee</hi> ſtumbled and fell and daſhed his foot againſt the ſtone. <hi>Leo in menſa, lepus in praelio:</hi> like many who crye out for warre, vnexpert in any thing but their heeles. <hi>Saxa memor retulit rurſus ad icta pedem.</hi> Seauen times in a day the iuſt man fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,<note place="margin">Luk. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.59.</note> but <hi>Peter</hi> three times in one houre denyeth his Maſter: hee had quickly come to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of 77. times a day, had God ſuffered him to go on, for at the laſt he began to curſe and ſweare, ſaying I know not the man.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.74. Ioh. 18.26.</note> he was ſtrongly temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. A Kinſman of him whoſe eare <hi>Peter</hi> cut off, ſpyeth him, <hi>Scribitque in marmore laeſus:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did not I ſee thee in the Garden with him? <hi>His valour, his Country, his ſpeech bewrayed him. Hoc
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15635:12"/>factumeſt magnae pietatis diſpenſatione, vt qui fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus erat Paſtor Eccleſiae, in ſua culpa diſceret, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter aliis miſereri debuiſſet,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory.</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was to inſtruct others,<note place="margin">Gr. ho. <hi>21.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatur in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ret. di. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> and how could hee with compaſſion, vnleſſe hee had firſt fallen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? Behold his reſurrection! <hi>Peter remembred the word of the Lord,</hi> how hee had ſaid vnto him, Before the Cock crow thou ſhalt deny me thriſe, and hee went out and wept bitterly. No maruell that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> fell ſo greeuouſly. Hee was but one. <hi>Woe to him that is alone.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 4.9.10.</note> Hee hath no man to helpe him. <hi>Epheſus</hi> is fallen; one of the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Cities of the world, the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of little <hi>Aſia,</hi> the glory of <hi>Ionia,</hi> built in the 28. yeare of <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. in Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic, Pauſan. as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Achaicis. Chriſ. praeſ. ad Epheſ. To. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. conc Eph. c. <hi>27.</hi> in Ep. ad cler. Constantinop. Lucian de Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teperegr.</note> either by the <hi>Amazons</hi> or one called <hi>Craeſus.</hi> Hence came <hi>Pythagoras, Parmenides, Zeno, Democritus.</hi> Heere <hi>Iohn</hi> and the <hi>Virgin</hi> liued. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus</hi> was renowned for the great temple of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana,</hi> one of the wonders of the World, 425. feet long, 220. broad, hauing 127. pillars the workes of ſo many Kings, 220. yeares in building, which <hi>Xerxes</hi> ſpared when hee burnt all the other Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Aſia,</hi> though <hi>Heroſtratus</hi> a baſe perſon, fired it on that day wherein <hi>Alexander</hi> was born at <hi>Pella,</hi> onely to make himſelfe famous. <hi>Epheſus</hi> became <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an omiſſion of good things, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing in her firſt loue, falling away. To ſearch the reaſons with <hi>Pererius</hi> were curious, <hi>whether</hi> they fell becauſe of the inſtability of free will, <hi>or</hi> becauſe no violent thing is perpetual, <hi>or</hi> becauſe Gods grace being ſupernaturall and in man, is in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15635:13"/>a ſtrange ſubiect: wee ſee their fall yet it is not finall. They are recouerable, elſe no reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brancer ſhould bee ſent vnto them. It is a moſt accurſed gloſſe of the <hi>Rhemiſts,</hi> that becauſe <hi>Epheſus</hi> left her firſt loue,<note place="margin">In Apoc.</note> therefore our opinion is refuted that a man once in grace and charity can neuer fall from it. I confeſſe many examples in holy Scripture are terrible to the weake Chriſtian. <hi>Dauid,</hi> whoſe conſcience once was ſo tender that hee cryed out, The Lord forbid that I ſhould ſtretch out mine hand againſt the anoynted of the Lord,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 24 6.</note> yet cauſeth <hi>Vriah</hi> to bee ſlaine. <hi>Noah</hi> preſerued in the deſtruction of the old World,<note place="margin">Ge. 7.7.19.16.9.21.19.33. In Pſ. 51.</note> and <hi>Lot</hi> in the ouerthrow of Sodome, were both ſhamefully drunke. <hi>Non cadendi exemplum propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum eſt, ſed ſi cecideris reſurgendi,</hi> Examples ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi> for our inſtruction, not that wee ſhould learne to fall, but hauing fallen to riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. There may be an <hi>Eclipſe</hi> of Gods graces in the beſt, but hee can neuer fall away finally or totally from faith.<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Whom God loueth hee loueth to the end.</hi> Hee that beleeueth on him hath euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but is paſſed from death vnto life, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. It may be with the child of God as it was with <hi>Eutichus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.24.</note> Hee fell into a deepe ſleepe,<note place="margin">Act. 20.9.12.</note> ſunke downe with ſleepe, and was taken vp dead, yet when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> fell on him, embracing him, hee ſaid trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not your ſelues, for his life is in him: and they brought the young man aliue. <hi>So Gods Child,</hi> in his owne eyes and the iudgement of others, may
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15635:13"/>ſeeme vtterly to fall from grace, but hee is built vpon the immouable rocke <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and the greateſt ſtormes of temptations cannot make him periſh,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.25.</note> Hee may <hi>diminiſh</hi> the good graces of God within him, elſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> had neuer exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Theſſalonians. Quench not the ſpirit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.19.</note> Hee may after repentance <hi>fall</hi> into the ſame ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, elſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> had neuer giuen that charge to the man that had beene ſicke thirty and eight yeares,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſinne no more leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</hi> Hee may ſin <hi>preſumptuouſly,</hi> that is willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in ſome ſort wilfully, elſe <hi>Dauid</hi> had neuer prayed,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.13.</note> 
               <hi>Keepe backe thy ſeruant alſo from preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſinnes.</hi> The Child of God may ſeeme to ſin <hi>deſperately,</hi> either through <hi>ignorance</hi> of his owne eſtate, or through <hi>horror</hi> of Conſcience for ſinnes committed, or through an often <hi>relapſe</hi> into ſome ſinne, or through a ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne vnworthines, or by abiuration of the truth through compulſion and feare. The inceſtuous Corinthian was like to be holden in this tranſgreſſion, and therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Corinthians to forgiue him, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him, leaſt perhaps hee ſhould bee ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp with ouermuch ſorrow. I am ſure poore <hi>Ionas</hi> was almoſt plunged in it: <hi>I am caſt out of thy ſight. Ion.</hi> 2. A dangerous concluſion,<note place="margin">Ion. 2.4.</note> a horrible ſinne, croſſing Gods loue which many waters cannot quench, neither can the flouds drowne it, Cap 8. It croſſeth his <hi>truth,</hi> which proclaimeth that if the wicked will <hi>turne from all his ſins that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 88.</note>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15635:14"/>
               <hi>hee hath committed,</hi> and keepe all his ſtatutes, and doe that which is lawfull and right, he ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>liue and not dye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ez. 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>Ez.</hi> 18. His <hi>power,</hi> which is able <hi>to ſubdue our iniquities, &amp; caſt all our ſins into the depthes of the ſea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 7.19.</note> 
               <hi>Mic.</hi> 7. <hi>His iuſtice,</hi> who hath <hi>layd vpon Chriſt the iniquity of vs all, Iſ.</hi> 53. His <hi>mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ. 53.6.</note> which vpon our returne will <hi>abundantly pardon</hi> Iſ. 55. A ſinne which beeing yeelded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in a <hi>Melancholique nature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ. 55.7.</note> 
               <hi>the Diuels forge,</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth many bloudy inſtruments into the hands of a man to deſtroy himſelfe.</p>
            <q>Quid nunc diuitiae? quid fului vaſta metalli Congeries?<note place="margin">Claudian.</note>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Heapes of gold and ſiluer, wife, Children, friends and pleaſures, ſeeme then miſerable comforters: but the elect yeeld not, God forbid they ſhould.</hi> Here were leaping from the panne into the fire.<note place="margin">Qui nihil poteſt ſperare, deſperet nihil. Sen. Miſericordiae Domini nec menſuras poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus conere, nec tempora defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Leo</note> 
               <hi>It is an vnlawfull, murtherous, damnable ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot,</hi> whether it be to preuent bondage, <hi>as Cato V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticenſis,</hi> becauſe he would not be in ſubiection to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> killed himſelfe: or <hi>Nero,</hi> being cenſured of the Senate: or when any thing falleth out contrary to expectation, as many <hi>hoorders</hi> vp of corne in dearths, ſeeing plenty: or to preuent ſinne and ſhame, as <hi>Lucretia,</hi> rauiſhed by <hi>Tarqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius:</hi> or prepoſterouſly deſiring to taſt of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, as <hi>Cleombrotus</hi> reading <hi>Platoes</hi> booke of the immortality of the ſoule: or vpon horror of Conſcience, as <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Iudas.</hi> For death is an enemie, and therefore not to be procured. The
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15635:14"/>Beaſts hurt not themſelues, and ſhall men? Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhould be neareſt vnto himſelfe.<note place="margin">1. Co. 15.26.</note> Our life is the guift of God, hee onely muſt reſume it. It is an iniury to the common wealth, the glory whereof is in the multitude of Subiects. Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arks, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, haue wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked another path,<note place="margin">Ber. de vita ſolit.</note> patiently wayting for a diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. <hi>Ionas</hi> was in a dangerous pang, yet at laſt ouercame. There is a <hi>veruntamen,</hi> a <hi>yet,</hi> or <hi>notwithſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tantam abſur ditate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do refutaſſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitror. Jer. Ep. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> which as the rudder in the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence turneth it another way. I will looke againe towards thy holy Temple: Gods child cannot fall finally, or vtterly: <hi>Gods fauour not depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon mans free will, but his owne free e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, whoſe decrees are vnalterable, and guifts without repentance.</hi> I might ſhew you here <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than againſt Sathan,</hi> the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> againſt the <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists: Viegas</hi> words croſſing the former gloſſe: <hi>Non amiſit charitatem, ſed de charitatis feruore nonnihil remiſit,</hi> Epheſus <hi>fell not from charity, but was not ſo hot as before.</hi> The mention of the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> opinion confuteth it: ſo of their other errours. The time would faile me to remember <hi>Rome</hi> of her great fall in many other particulars.<note place="margin">Au. l. de vnit. Eccl. c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Her miracles</hi> being like the wonders of the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, in S <hi>Augustines</hi> times, <hi>Aut figmenta men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacium hominum aut portenta fallacium ſpirituum, Either fictions of lying men, or fantaſies of drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Deuils. Claudius Eſpencaeus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>dig.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> their owne wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confeſſeth: No ſtable is ſo full of dung, as the Legends full of fables: yea fictions are contained
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15635:15"/>in their Porteſſes. They haue fallen from the faith in Miracles.<note place="margin">Sacramental. li. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>30</hi>
               </note> Their <hi>Merits</hi> is a doctrine of <hi>Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme,</hi> ſaith <hi>Waldenſis;</hi> neuer allowed (ſaith iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Perkins</hi>) of the ſound profeſſors for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares after <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Romes <hi>Cuſanus</hi> maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,<note place="margin">Dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Probl. cir. Excit. l. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Chriſts</hi> death was onely of abilitie to merit eternall life. They haue fallen from the faith in merits. So in <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> another twig ariſing from the ſame roote, then which no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is more iniurious to the death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> wherein it were a ſhame to ſpeake what <hi>Suarez,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>To.</hi> 1. <hi>diſp.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Durand,</hi> and other groſſer Papiſts haue diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But their <hi>Bayus</hi> ſticketh not to grant, that there is but one ſatisfaction only vnto God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De indulg. t. vlt.</note> Let them remember how they haue fallen in ſatisfaction. So in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> worthy of a Satyre, which <hi>Luther</hi> in a frumpe called <hi>Stercus humanum:</hi> Popiſh Doctors cannot agree among themſelues of the fire, the torments, the ſubiects, the duration, the exequutioners, the condition of the ſoules there detained. It was vnknowne to the Church 1100. yeares after <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Their <hi>Suarez</hi> denieth their greateſt argument,<note place="margin">To. <hi>4.</hi> in Th. d. <hi>46.</hi>
               </note> the walking Ghoſts of the dead. They muſt remember whence they haue fallen into Purgatorie. So in their <hi>Inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Saints, and number of <hi>Mediatours,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time making <hi>Chriſt S. Francis,</hi> and S. <hi>Francis Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Turſelline.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>I am Franciſcus erit qui modo Christus erat.</q>
            <p>A tongue worthy to be cut out of his mouth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15635:15"/>while he liued, as <hi>Ierom</hi> ſpake of his <hi>Vigilantius.</hi> Hence came the 7. ceremonies of canonizing to be inſcribed in a Calender with redde letters, praying, erecting Churches,<note place="margin">Bell. de ſanct. Beatit. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>8</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Dices.</note> miniſtring the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, and ſaying Canonicall howers to them and in their honour, dedicating holy daies, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp Images, and worſhiping their Reliques: yet the Saints canonized may be no Saints; and the miracles, whereupon their canonization is grounded, may be falſe, ſaith their <hi>Caietan.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers complain,<note place="margin">Tract. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. et de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent.</note> they haue worſhipped many for Saints in heauen, who may be preſumed to be tormented with the Diuells in hell. They haue fallen in his. So in their <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to ouerthrow the truth of <hi>Chriſts</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, which maketh vs cry out in much paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as <hi>Auerroes</hi> ieſted of old, <hi>Is it poſſible that Christians ſhould make themſelues a God of bread?</hi> An errour contayning as many abſurdities, as there haue bene minuts of time from the firſt forming of it (that is from the Councell of <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rane</hi>) vntill this hower.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1215.</note> They haue fallen in their precepts and practiſe of <hi>eqiuuocation,</hi> and <hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall reſeruation:</hi> worſe herein then the <hi>Diuell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Reu. B. of Saliſbury in his Sermon called The old way.</note> for hee equiuocated to hide his ignorance of that which he could not reueale: theſe equiuocate to hide their knowledg of that they an and ought to reueale. In their <hi>King-killing doctrine:</hi> In their aſſertions, that Dogs, &amp; Mice, and Swine, eating their conſecrated Hoſt,<note place="margin">Aq. p. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>80.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> do eate into their bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els the very body and blood of Chriſt. That it is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15635:16"/>more lawfull for a <hi>Prieſt</hi> to commit fornication,<note place="margin">Coſter. enchir. c. <hi>15.</hi> Rota: indeciſ. <hi>1.</hi> Nu. <hi>3.</hi> in No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſſ.</note> then to marry a wife: That the <hi>Popes power</hi> is greater then the Apoſtles. And that the Pope may derogate from the Apoſtles ſayings. That the <hi>holy Scripture,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſius de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe verbo Dei.</note> 
               <hi>as it is aleaged of Catholiques is the word of God, but as it is aleaged of Heretiques (ſo they call Protestants)</hi> is the expreſſe word of the Diuell. Heer is the marke of a reprobate illuſion: <hi>They receiue not the loue of the truth, that they might be ſaued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſſ 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>therefore they belieue lies, that they may be damned.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 2. I leaue them to God, &amp; come neerer to our ſelues. <hi>Remember &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> A <hi>Leſſon</hi> to reproue many prodigall Sinners, who runne ſo long vpon the ſcore of Sathan, that they can neuer indure to heare of a recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and remembrancer. Like <hi>Dicaearchus</hi> the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, who becauſe it was hard for him to conceiue what the nature or properties of the ſoule were,<note place="margin">Tull. Tuſe.</note> therefore affirmed the ſoule to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. So theſe, becauſe they haue loſt the ſenſe and ſting of ſinne, thinke nothing they doe to be ſinne, though, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpake of the drunkard, they be all ſinne. How many are there who think, that becauſe they are not as bad as others, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are good enough. Hence is it that the offers of Gods mercie are ſo diſdainefully enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and ſo commonly reiected. Men, not knowing their owne neceſſity, <hi>doe deſpiſe the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Gods bountie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> 
               <hi>and tread vnder feet the ſonne of God. Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>One</hi> coloureth a groſſe ſinne with a tolerable name, that ſo either it may not be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15635:16"/>ſeene, or may not appeare in its owne likenes, calling <hi>haughtines</hi> magnanimity, <hi>ignorance</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie,<note place="margin">Aug. conſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> Sen. ep. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>hereſie</hi> deepe learning, <hi>Machiaueliani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſme,</hi> pollicie, <hi>giddineſse</hi> zeale, <hi>furie</hi> manhood, <hi>oppreſſion</hi> the making the moſt of a mans owne, <hi>Vſury,</hi> intereſt, or vſage, or putting out, any thing ſaue plaine vſurie. <hi>Another</hi> draweth a falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion out of Gods mercie, and will continue in ſinne, <hi>that grace may abound:</hi> like the Diuels concluſion to our Sauiour, <hi>Caſt thy ſelfe downe, for the Angels ſhal beare the vp:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 4 6.</note> as if a man ſhould poyſon himſelfe, preſuming vpon a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſon, or deſperately ſurfeit becauſe he is nere to a <hi>Phyſitian. Dauid</hi> confeſſed, <hi>There is forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with thee that thou maiſt be feared. Pſa.</hi> 130.<note place="margin">Pſ. 130 4.</note> But theſe vſe it as if it made God neglected. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> runne on in all kinds of riot, hoping to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie for all by ſome ſpeciall deuotions. A <hi>deuice</hi> by which many worldlings deceiue themſelues, who hauing by rapine and extortion, by grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the faces of the poore, and eating them vp as if they were bread, raked much together, imagine to remedie all this with God and the world by ſome largeſſe to the poore, and therfore wil ſtick at no violent &amp; indirect courſe. <hi>(I pray God I be not now in ſome of your boſoms that heare me this day)</hi> S. <hi>Austin</hi> propoundeth the caſe thus: The <hi>Extortioner</hi> ſaith thus vnto me,<note place="margin">De verb. Apo. ſer. <hi>21.</hi> to. <hi>10</hi>
               </note> I am not like the rich man in the Goſpell, I feaſt the poore, I ſend ſuſtenance to the priſoners, I cloath the naked, I entertaine the ſtrangers: to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15635:17"/>whom he anſwereth, <hi>Dare te putas, tollere noli et dedisti, Thou thinkeſt thou giueſt, doe not take away and thou haſt giuen.</hi> Hee reioyceth to whom thou haſt giuen, but hee weepeth, from whom thou haſt taken away. It is not ſufficient to ceaſe from euill, but wee muſt learne to doe good. It is not enough to ſtand ſtill in the path of goodnes, but wee muſt goe on.</p>
            <p>Euery man muſt examine himſelfe, ſearch out his owne wants, and remember from whence hee is fallen. Elſe, <hi>if men fall</hi> and will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, if they turne away and will not returne, <hi>if they ſlide backe, if they repent not</hi> of their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſaying, what haue we done? euery one turning to his courſe as the horſe ruſheth into the battaile: <hi>Their wiues ſhall be giuen vnto other men, and their fields vnto them that ſhall inherit them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ie. 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>Ier.</hi> 8. Had I the <hi>voyce</hi> of more then a man, and louder then a <hi>Trumpet,</hi> I would cry vnto all the world, as S. <hi>Iohn vnto Epheſus, Remember from whence thou art fallen. Miſerrimum est fuiſſe beatum, It is moſt wofull to haue beene happy.</hi> O it is a great miſery to haue been <hi>zealous,</hi> and now to bee <hi>luke-warme: to haue put our hands to the Plough, and now to looke back:</hi> to haue a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning laudable, but an end damnable. Doth not thy owne ſoule proclaim thee guilty? neither do I: but <hi>be not deceiued,</hi> God is not mocked, <hi>Wee all</hi> either goe forward or backward. If wee fall back: As in the dayes that were before the flood, They were eating and drinking, marrying, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15635:17"/>giuing in marriage, vntill the day that <hi>Noah</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Arke,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.38.39.</note> and knew not vntill the flood came and tooke them all away: So ſhall the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Sonne of man be vnto vs, except wee remember from whence wee haue fallen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>An inſtruction</hi> to vs all to recollect our beſt thoughts for our forepaſſed liues.<note place="margin">Iſ. 1.3.</note> Shall the <hi>Oxe</hi> know his owner, and the <hi>Aſse</hi> his maiſters cribb: ſhal the <hi>Storke</hi> in the heauens know her appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted times, and the <hi>Turtle,</hi> and the <hi>Craine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ie. 8.7.</note> and the <hi>Swallow</hi> obſerue the time of their comming: &amp; ſhall not we conſider the paſſages of our liues? Doe wee with <hi>Agathocles</hi> (a Potters ſonne, made a King) carry about vs <hi>earthen veſsels,</hi> which may remember vs of our mortality, and yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get death? Shall it be with vs as in the time of <hi>Simonides,</hi> who complayned, that after the vſe of letters was inuented, the vertue of memory decayed? The more the Goſpell is preached, and mercy offered, ſhall wee be the more dull? <hi>Bleſsed Chriſtian,</hi> bee not like a painted <hi>Tombe,</hi> guilded without, rotten within, tipping thy <hi>tongue</hi> with godlines, and filling thy <hi>ſoule</hi> with bitternes, bearing a <hi>bible</hi> in thy hand, and <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in thy heart: Remember thy oath in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> many vowes and reſolutions ſince. <hi>If wee haue broke them wee muſt be anſwerable vnto God.</hi> It is not with vs, as it was with <hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi> who, in prolonging the time, ſtayed &amp; aſſuaged by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees the fiercenes of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> and by delay deliuered the commonwealth of <hi>Rome.</hi> For God
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15635:18"/>cannot indure delay in heauenly matters. O then <hi>Now</hi> ſit downe, looke vpon thy life, catechiſe thy ſelfe as he did, <hi>Anima quid fecisti hodie?</hi> O my ſoule what haſt thou done? If with <hi>Demas</hi> wee haue forſaken <hi>Paul</hi> whom once wee loued,<note place="margin">2 Ti. 4.10.</note> and are intangled in the world, <hi>Let vs remember from whence we haue fallen.</hi> If with <hi>Peter</hi> we haue failed in our true ſeruice vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this word of my Text, <hi>Remember</hi> that this life is but <hi>horoe momentum,</hi> yet in this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an hower we ſaue or looſe all. O before thy weake dayes come, wherein one poore <hi>Ague</hi> or ſome other diſeaſe, ſhall ſhake all the frame of the houſe, ſumme vp thy thoughts, words, actions, before the time come wherein thou muſt await the heauy doome of the <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> as the thiefe doth the ſentence of the Iudge: when flegme and ſpittle ſhall ſo wofully beſiedge thy life, beſides <hi>groanes, ſtitches, cold ſweat and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings:</hi> thou muſt then forget thy fathers houſe, and leaue all the world: therefore let this day be vnto vs all as if it were our laſt. Let not ſin <hi>reign</hi> in our mortall bodies,<note place="margin">Heb. 10 27.</note> for if wee ſinne <hi>wilfully</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we haue receiued the knowledg of the truth, there remaineth <hi>no more ſacrifice for ſinnes,</hi> but a <hi>certaine</hi> fearefull looking for of iudgement, and fiery indignation. <hi>Repentance</hi> is our guide, and therefore <hi>Repent and doe the firſt workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a man read ouer the morall writings of ſome <hi>Heathens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pri. ſec.</note> he would pitty them, to ſee their witty and carefull diſquiſition of true reſt lead
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15635:18"/>them to much vnquietnes. They are like wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <hi>Empiricks,</hi> which in tables and pictures make great oſtentation of cures, yet can neuer approue their ſkill to their credulous Patients. Many <hi>wrote</hi> of it, none attained it. Some pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced true <hi>tranquilitie</hi> in a <hi>conſtant</hi> eſtate of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thinges; whereas theſe varie as often as the weather, being <hi>got with care, kept with feare, loſt with ſorrow. Others,</hi> in ſuch a <hi>temper</hi> of the ſoule, as that it ſhould neuer be affected with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny caſuall euents; whereas, while it is priſoner in the <hi>Dungeon</hi> of fleſh and blood,<note place="margin">Seu. de Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quill.</note> it is one while <hi>chearefull,</hi> another while <hi>dull, drowſie, comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi> prone to reſt, loathing former reſolutions. <hi>Others</hi> hold the beſt way for peace to be, when a man <hi>imployeth</hi> himſelf in ſome publike affaires, then retyreth himſelfe to his priuate ſtudies, thinking vpon the tryall of his ability, nature of his buſineſſes, choiſe of his friends, fore-imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the worſt in all caſuall matters; <hi>Nay further,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. c vlt.</note> in making the <hi>moſt</hi> of himſelfe, chearing vp his ſpirits with the variety of recreations, and other indulgences. <hi>Miſerable</hi> comforters are all theſe. Here is no mention of the greateſt enemies, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> of euill done, and <hi>feare</hi> of euill to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. Can any man haue peace that is at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with God and himſelfe? Or is that peace the peace of God, which is thought to be with out him? <hi>Epheſus</hi> is better inſtructed, <hi>Repent and doe the firſt workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Jn aureis car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus.</note>
               <hi>Pythagoras</hi> aduiſed, that euery mans exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15635:19"/>in priuate ſhould runne vpon three Art<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,<note place="margin">Jn anrcis car. minibus.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> wherein wee haue <hi>tranſgreſsed,</hi> that wee may repent; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> what good wee haue done that wee may hold out, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> what wee haue <hi>omitted</hi> which wee ſhould haue done. <hi>My ſecond circumſtance is more direct,</hi> in as great a <hi>Laconiſme,</hi> and as perfect breuity as can poſſibly be deſcribed. And therefore as <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> ſpake of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> booke <hi>de mundo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Apol.</note> which he wrote to <hi>Alexander,</hi> that it was the Epitome of all his Philoſophie: So may wee of this leſſon of <hi>S. Iohn to Epheſus,</hi> It is the ſumme of all his Diuinitie. <hi>Repent.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Where if I would be contentious about words, that cauill of <hi>Gregory Martin</hi> might giue ſufficient occaſion who taxeth reuerend <hi>Beza,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Mart. in a booke inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled, A diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry &amp;c. aunſ. by D. Fulke.</note> for tranſlating the word <hi>Reſipiſce,</hi> which (ſaith hee) ſhould be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred as the Vulgar, <hi>Age poenitentiam. I anſwer,</hi> wee <hi>refuſe</hi> thoſe words which they tranſlate, <hi>Doe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> becauſe they meane thereby <hi>ſatiſfaction</hi> for ſinnes paſt to be a neceſſary part of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; which is not contained in the Greeke word, ſignifying onely a <hi>change</hi> of the minde, that is, not onely a ſorrow for the ſinne paſt, but a purpoſe of amendment, which is beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the Latin word <hi>Reſipiſcere,</hi> which is alwaies taken in good part, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> whereas the latine word <hi>poenitere</hi> and <hi>poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia,</hi> may and are vſed in latin of ſorrow and repentance that are too late, as of <hi>Iudas</hi> griefe of minde, which cauſed him to hang himſelfe:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15635:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>but not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Reſipiſcere</hi> and <hi>Reſipiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia:</hi> and therefore the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſpeaking of his ſorrow, vſeth another word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. We abhorre that tranſlation which main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth ſatiſfaction for ſinnes by any ſuffering of ours, as <hi>blaſphemous</hi> to the ſatisfaction of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe <hi>blood onely</hi> cleanſeth vs from all ſin.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.7.</note> If the word <hi>Satisfaction</hi> were vſed by any fathers of the Church, <hi>It was not that they had any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſatiſfie the iuſtice of God by externall works, but that by thoſe outward tryals of their repentance, the Church was ſatisfied, which by their fall was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended:</hi> &amp; the gouernours of the Church, by ſuch ſignes of true ſorrow and amendment, were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to receiue them againe into the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, from whence vntill ſufficient tryall had of their repentance, they were ſeparated &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. But I remember my Text is <hi>doctrinall and morall, Repent and doe the firſt workes:</hi> whence this <hi>collection</hi> neceſſarily ariſeth.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Repentance</hi> and the practiſe of a holy life,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> are the direct meanes whereby ſinners are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vnto God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>proofs</hi> heereof are ſo many and pregnant throughout both <hi>Teſtaments,</hi> that whatſoeuer is there written may ſerue for a teſtimony. Al the <hi>Sermons</hi> of Prophets and Apoſtles proclaime this. This was the charg of <hi>Ezekiel: Say vnto them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>As I liue ſaith the Lord God, I haue no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turne from his way and liue. Turne yee, turne ye from your
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15635:20"/>euill waies, for why will ye dye O houſe of Iſraell. Ez.</hi> 33. <hi>This</hi> was the ſubiect of the preaching of <hi>Iſai. Waſh yee, make you cleane, Put away the euill of your doings from before your eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1. Of <hi>Ieremy, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne ye now euery one from his euill way, and make your wayes and your doings good. Ie.</hi> 18.<note place="margin">Ie. 18.11.</note> Of <hi>Hoſea, O Iſraell returne vnto the Lord thy God, for thou haſt fallen by thy iniquity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of.</hi> 14.1. Mat. 3.2. Mat. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. Of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, <hi>Repent yee for the kingdome of heauen is at hand. Mat.</hi> 4. Of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of whoſe preaching was <hi>Repent. Mat-</hi> 4. <hi>This</hi> was the <hi>end</hi> of his paſſion and reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>repentance and remiſſion of ſinnes ſhould bee preached in his name amongſt all Nations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lu. 24.47.</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How</hi> many <hi>promiſes</hi> are added vnto this! <hi>If thou wilt put a way thine abhominations out of my ſight, then ſhalt thou not remoue. Ier.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Ie. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>If the wicked re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the pledge, giue againe that hee hath robbed, walke in the Statutes of life without committing iniquity, hee ſhall ſurely liue bee ſhall not die. None of his ſinnes that hee hath committed, ſhall bee men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned vnto him: if hee hath done that which is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and right,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ez 33.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſhall ſurely liue. Ez.</hi> 33.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iob</hi> prayed for this: <hi>a ſpace to repent. Are not my dayes few, ceaſe then and let me alone that I may take comfort a little, before I goe whence I ſhall not returne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 10 20.21.</note> 
               <hi>euen to the land of darknes, &amp; the ſhadow of death. Iob.</hi> 10. <hi>Vnto this</hi> the <hi>goodnes of</hi> God lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>death vs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> It remoued the <hi>plague</hi> from Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell.<note place="margin">Ki. 24.16.17.</note> 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 24. brought <hi>deliuerance</hi> vnto the Iewes,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15635:20"/>when <hi>Shiſhak</hi> King of Egypt came againſt them with twelue hundred Chariots, and three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore thouſand horſemen, and Egyptians without number. 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 12.<note place="margin">2. Ch. 12, 3.</note> It ſtayed iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from <hi>Pharaoh: For</hi> when hee ſaw the <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> anoyed with the firſt plague, the <hi>Earth</hi> with the ſecond and third, and the <hi>Aire</hi> with the fourth,<note place="margin">Dr. Hall cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templat.</note> (a winged Army comming from an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry God, not from Nature or chance) finding it impoſſible for him to ſtand out with God, ſince all his power could not reſcue him from his leaſt Creatures, his heart begins to thaw, ſaying to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Goe and doe ſacrifice in this Land, or becauſe that had beene an Abhomination, Goe into the wildernes,</hi> but not farre. He will not leaue them: <hi>But</hi> when the voyce of Gods thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and haile, mixed with fire, rouze him vp, then (as betwixt ſleeping and waking) hee ſtarts vp, <hi>I haue ſinned this time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ero. 19.34.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord is righteous and I and my people are wicked.</hi> Meere neceſſity conſtrained him to relent: <hi>For</hi> the <hi>Fiſh</hi> beeing deſtroyed with the firſt blow, the <hi>Cattell</hi> with the fifth, the <hi>Corne</hi> with the ſeauenth, the <hi>fruit</hi> and <hi>leaues</hi> with this eight, and now nothing left him but a bare fruitleſſe earth, to liue vpon, he was mollified: and howſoeuer conſtrained re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance bee euer ſhort and vnſound, yet vpon <hi>Moſes</hi> prayer the thunders and haile ceaſed. But this repentance is not that which can preuaile. So <hi>Caine</hi> repented, <hi>My puniſhment is greater then I can beare, Gen.</hi> 4. <hi>From thy face ſhall I bee hid;</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15635:21"/>Hee knew that <hi>Nihil grauius quam errantem a Deo deſeri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Caine &amp; Abel c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vt ſe reuocare non poſſet. Nothing is more grieuous, then for him that erreth to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of God, that he cannot recall himſelfe.</hi> So did <hi>Saul</hi> repent, <hi>Ieroboam, Ahab, Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira, Agrippa, Foelix, Simon Magus, Elimas. But</hi> the true practiſe of a right repentance conſiſteth in an <hi>inward</hi> ſorrow, when we are diſpleaſed with our ſelues for ſinnes; and in an <hi>outward,</hi> when we teſtifie it by teares and ſuch like; <hi>when</hi> we reſolue <hi>to ſinne no more,</hi> but to doe the good and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table will of God; when with <hi>humiliation</hi> there is <hi>faith</hi> added; when wee <hi>grieue</hi> that wee cannot grieue enough. The <hi>Angels</hi> in Heauen ſing at this lamentation, neither doth the earth afford any ſo ſweet Muſicke in the eares of God. <hi>Many</hi> may be vexed with an extreme remorſe for ſome ſinne from the gripes of a galled Conſcience, playing at once the <hi>Accuſer, Witnes, Iudge, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentor,</hi> and yet neuer know the power of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. But an earneſt <hi>ſorrow</hi> for the want of <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> was neuer found in any but a gracious heart, whoſe teares are as the raine in a Sunne-ſhine, comfortable and hopefull.</p>
            <p>This is that which <hi>melts</hi> vs, <hi>purgeth</hi> vs, <hi>rinſeth</hi> vs, and ſo <hi>maketh</hi> vs of droſſie, pure; of foggy ſound; of crooked, ſtreight Chriſtians. And as <hi>impure gold</hi> cannot be <hi>rid of the droſſe,</hi> vntill it be moulten and diſſolued,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> neither vnſound bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies full of vicious humors come to any good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate till they are wel <hi>purged:</hi> No more can we, till
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15635:21"/>
               <hi>Repentance</hi> breake vs, and cauſe vs to doe our firſt workes. This remembreth vs of good omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and euill committed.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sum Dea quae facti, non factique exigo poenas,<note place="margin">Auſonius Gallus in paroemia.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Nempe vt poeniteat, ſic Metanoia vocor.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This is like the riuer <hi>Nilus</hi> which turned furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Io</hi> into a glorious <hi>Virgin: Dauid, Ezekiah, Manaſses, Mary Magdalen,</hi> the <hi>Prodigall, Zache,</hi> the Iewes are examples. It is like the <hi>ſea,</hi> prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the vomit and loathing of our ſinnes. It is like the <hi>ſand,</hi> ſtaying the violent rage of the waues of our tranſgreſſions; like the herbe <hi>Century,</hi> bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſweet; bitter in meditation of Gods iudgements, ſweet in imbracing his mercies; like a <hi>thunderbolt</hi> extinguiſhing the corruption and poyſon of our Serpentine nature; like an <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,</hi> whoſe trembling is a filiall feare, whoſe rent &amp; ſciſſure is the breaking of the heart, whoſe ſound is a crying voyce, whoſe motion is a grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in grace, whoſe winds are temptations, and the duſt is the remembrance of our mortality. <hi>Repentance</hi> is our Armour to quench all the fiery Darts of the fleſh, world, and Deuill. It is as <hi>Hilary</hi> ſheweth,<note place="margin">Hil. in p <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ab eo quod poenitendum intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexeris deſtitiſſe,</hi> a ceaſing from that which wee vnderſtand muſt bee repented of. It is <hi>proeterita mala plangere, &amp; plangenda iterum non committe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> a mourning for ſinnes committed, and a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe neuer to commit them being to bee lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Languores ſanat, leproſos curat, mortuos ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, &amp;c.</hi> as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſweetly.<note place="margin">Aug. l. de poenit.</note> It healeth fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15635:22"/>cureth lepers,<note place="margin">Aug. l. de poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it.</note> raiſeth the dead, encreaſeth health, maketh the lame to goe, the blind to ſee, expelleth vices, and comforteth the Soule of a Chriſtian. It is the medicine of our wounds, the hope of Saluation,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fid. Aetim. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>per quam peccatores ſaluantur, Deus ad miſericordiam prouocatur,</hi> by which ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are redeemed and God is prouoked to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. It is <hi>iugum ſuaue &amp; leue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ſup. Pſ.</note> 
               <hi>quia non eſt ſarcina viatoris ſed ala volatoris,</hi> A ſweet and light yoak, not a burthen for vs trauailers, but a wing to make vs all fliers to Gods Kingdome. It is our ſecond <hi>lauer</hi> of regeneration, the onely rebaptization, allowed in diuinity, conſiſting <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Chryſ. in Ro. <hi>12</hi>
               </note> as well in the contrition of the heart as the reformation of the mind. <hi>Repentance</hi> is the <hi>Chriſtalline</hi> humor of the eye of faith,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the beſt <hi>Aqua-vitae</hi> to reuiue our dead ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that <hi>Aqua coeleſtis</hi> which God keepeth in his bottle that not one drop of it can bee loſt, and it is the <hi>brine</hi> wherewith both fleſh and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit muſt bee kept from tainture and corruption, therefore preſcribed vnto <hi>Epheſus, Repent and doe the first workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> 1. A <hi>Caueat</hi> for vs to beware of the leauen of the Romiſh Synagogue, whereby they offer much wrong vnto this holy ordinance of God. I ſhall but touch on ſome points of their greateſt Patrons, <hi>aiming</hi> rather at our owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling with God, then quarrelling with ſuch obſtinate Aduerſaries, who as they may well ſeeme to haue no <hi>faith,</hi> annihilating it by merit
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15635:22"/>of workes; no <hi>hope,</hi> weakening it by doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſaluation; no <hi>Religion</hi> as it is the true knowledge of the true God, concealing this from the people, by cauſing the Scriptures in a ſtrange tranſlation, or as it is the ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of one God, defiling the purity and diuiding the integrity thereof by that <hi>latrioduliacall</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Idols Adoration, and Saints inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; no <hi>Charity,</hi> witneſſe their Gunpowder plot; ſo they haue no <hi>Repentance,</hi> avoyding it by their Indulgences. Sometimes they make it a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, becauſe it is the net that taketh all their prouiſion: and yet they know not when or where it was inſtituted or who commanded it.<note place="margin">L. cum de lege ff de proba. &amp; Gloſſ. Ibid. Coll. Ratiſp. Anno <hi>1601.</hi> habitum <hi>Mat. 12.3. Mat. 15.3.4.</hi> Aug. <hi>10.9.</hi> de Catachſ. c <hi>4.</hi> p. c. <hi>75.</hi> Edit. Ba. <hi>1529.</hi> Cypr. Ep. l. <hi>2.</hi> Ep. <hi>1.</hi> ad Steph. p. <hi>42.</hi> Ed t. Baſ. <hi>15 30.</hi> Just. Mart. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. <hi>2.</hi> Tertull. cont Marcion. l. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>4.</hi> Amb. de Sacr. Cyrill. in Myſtagogitis Alexa. <hi>4.</hi> q <hi>8.</hi> m. <hi>2.</hi> Art. <hi>1.</hi> Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u. quem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Ouand. q. d. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> They affirme it, wee denye it, and the ciuill law conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that <hi>Probatio incumbit affirmanti,</hi> and the Ieſuits confeſſed it <hi>in colloquio Ratiſbonenſi,</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> proued that doctrine which hee affirmed as the plucking and eating of the eares of corne by his hungry Diſciples <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. The Phariſes to be tranſgreſſors of the law, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. In the 20. ver. he denyeth that to eat with vnwaſhen hands defileth a man, hee leaueth the Affirmatiue part to the Phariſes to proue. <hi>Antiquity</hi> is againſt their ſeauen Sacraments, <hi>Aug. To.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp; Cypr. Ep. l.</hi> 2. Beſides <hi>Iuſt. Martyr, Tertullian, Ambroſe, Cyrillus Alexandrinus:</hi> I leaue the ground of it, their <hi>priuat Confeſſion,</hi> which the Ieſuits <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> of the text ſeeme to proue, from <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.23. But <hi>Alexander Bonauenture,</hi> and <hi>Fr. Ouand.</hi> deny that euer Chriſt ordained it: nay for the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15635:23"/>ſpace of a thouſand yeares after <hi>Chriſt</hi> and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, it was not reckoned amongſt the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. They ouerthrow the nature of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, by giuing ſo much liberty to ſinne, holding that <hi>Priſoners</hi> may breake the Iayle: a poynt practiſed by Romiſh Prieſts amongſt vs. <hi>Caietan</hi> defendeth it,<note place="margin">Calet. <hi>22.</hi> pag. <hi>144.</hi> Tolet. ſum. pag. <hi>548.</hi> Gl. v. multorum Can. vidua. diſt. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> That Children may marry without conſent of Parents. That ſhee onely is <hi>meretricious,</hi> that hath polluted her ſelfe with more then twenty and three thouſand men. It is their damnable gloſſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Magne Regnator Deûm tam lentus audis ſcelera?</l>
               <l>Tam le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus vides? Ecqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do ſaeua fulme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> emittes manu?</l>
            </q>
            <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
            <p>Hee that reads <hi>Nauarrs</hi> Manuall, ſhall find <hi>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick</hi> blaſphemy a veniall ſinne, <hi>pag.</hi> 91. ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heft veniall <hi>p.</hi> 140. common <hi>lying</hi> veniall <hi>p.</hi> 191. <hi>curſing</hi> of Parents, if not malicious, veniall <hi>p.</hi> 100. And theſe Venialls (ſaith <hi>Francis a Victoria</hi>) by a <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> or ſprinckling of holy water, or knock of the breaſt are cleared. Let theſe pretend perfection Euangelicall neuer ſo much, whereby (as the Aſſe with the Lyons skin on his backe) they gull the ignorant, yet you ſee what large Conſciences they haue: Theſe are their workes: examples of their enioyned penance are infinite.<note place="margin">M. Fox p. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>141.</hi>
               </note> King <hi>Edgar</hi> was inioyned by <hi>Dunſtan</hi> not to wear his Crowne in ſeauen yeares, for deflouring a Virgin: The carrying of a <hi>Fagot</hi> was an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry penance vpon this day vnto this place.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 671.</note> The carrying before the Proceſſion bagges of ſtraw,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P:</hi> 511.</note>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:15635:23"/>for not bringing <hi>litera</hi> (the Popiſh latin word) for a popiſh Prelats horſes.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onfinius l. <hi>1.</hi> Occad. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hildebrand</hi> commanded <hi>Conradus</hi> a German comming a penitent to Rome to weare a coat of Maile in ſtead of his ſhirt, and faſtened it with fiue chains, giuing him ſealed letters containing the Catalogue of his ſinnes, and commanding him to viſit all the holy places of the earth. Are theſe their firſt workes?</p>
            <p>They ouerthrow the nature of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, by their <hi>prodigall</hi> grants and ſhamefull Martes of Pardons:<note place="margin">Cap. inter ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a charitatis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſponſ. l. <hi>4.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cretal.</note> giuing a Pardon for all ſuch men as ſhall take common Women out of the <hi>Stewes</hi> and marry them. A pardon for twenty thouſand dayes by the grant of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 6. for ſaying one <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> at the eleuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">M. White in is way to the Church. P. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>55</hi> &amp; <hi>256.</hi>
               </note> A pardon for 6666. dayes, as many dayes ſay they as <hi>Chriſt</hi> had wounds in his body, for ſaying a prayer as long as three <hi>Auees</hi> before the Crucifixe. A pardon for <hi>forty thouſand yeares,</hi> by Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 4. to him that would ſay a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his making, not fiue aboue 40. words long. A pardon of <hi>forty dayes</hi> to him that bright a faggot,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ox p <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>897.</hi>
               </note> or but a ſtake to the burning of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. A pardon to any man to deliuer one ſoul out of Purgatory for <hi>ten ſhillings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 771.</note> by <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, in the yeare of our Lord 1516. If there be any one in this great <hi>Congregation,</hi> intoxicate with the Popiſh potions of Rome, let him ſee what mercie is in the Pope, who holding that it is in his power to call miſerable ſoules out of this tormenting fire (which hell it ſelfe is ſaid
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15635:24"/>to exceed onely in the continuance) yet that he ſhould ſuffer them to lye houling there, and not mercifully beſtow on them all the heaps of his treaſure, as the ſpirituall ranſome of ſo many diſtreſſed Spirits. O <hi>inhumane acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of perſons, that the wealthier ſort may by their purſes deliuer others from this priſon, while the needy ſoule muſt be ſtill frying in that flame, without all hope of pardon vntill the very laſt iudgement day! But I remember their own men doubt whether there be a Purgatory, and <hi>wee</hi> knowe there is none: and they conclude, that the <hi>Pope</hi> may lead with him innumerable ſouls to hell to periſh with him for euer (much more leaue ſome in Purgatory if there were any) yet may no mortall man take vpon him to reproue him.<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>40.50.</hi> Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>apa.</note> Thus Babilon, I meane <hi>Rome</hi> is fallen, yet ſhee remembreth not that ſhe is fallen, ſhe will not repent, you ſee her workes, wee would haue healed her but ſhe refuſed.</p>
            <p>Yet let vs be here <hi>admoniſhed</hi> to conſider our owne waies,<note place="margin">Vſe. 2.</note> and looking vpon our firſt workes, <hi>bring</hi> forth fruite worthy amendment of life. (<hi>Bleſſed</hi> and <hi>beloued</hi> Chriſtians) Wee cannot be ſo happy as <hi>Tullies</hi> wiſe man,<note place="margin">Tull. Tuſc.</note> to doe nothing for which we need to repent; as <hi>Iſidore</hi> which vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily proteſted, that for forty yeares ſpace he found not in himſelfe any ſinne, not ſo much as in his thought, not ſo much as any conſent to anger or inordinate deſire:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr. Hall.</hi> No peace with Rome. <hi>Tit. de</hi>
               </note> a teſtimony giuen to <hi>Gonzaga</hi> for ſome yeares that late Saint by <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:15635:24"/>and <hi>Bellarmine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Justificat. Qu. vitam e. ius.</note> The <hi>offall</hi> of the ſchooles may hold of <hi>Bonauenture,</hi> that in him <hi>non peccauit Adam, Adam ſinned not.</hi> Let <hi>Manichoeus</hi> proteſt it of his Maiſters, <hi>Priſcallian, Euagrius, Iouinian;</hi> the <hi>Meſsalians</hi> of themſelues: Wee muſt all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue as S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> not to boaſt becauſe we are iuſt, but becauſe wee are redeemed, not becauſe wee are void of ſinne, but becauſe our ſinnes are forgiuen vs. But without <hi>repentance</hi> and doing the former workes, there is no remiſſion of ſins; <hi>Repentance,</hi> the guift of God, ioy of Angels, hauen of ſinners. <hi>Awake</hi> thou that ſleepeſt in thy ſinnes,<note place="margin">2. Ti. 2.7.</note> I ſay vnto thee as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Tymothy,</hi> Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord giue thee vnderſtanding in all things. <hi>Come</hi> now and reaſon with God, though thy ſinnes be as ſcarlet, they may be as white as ſnow,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1.18.</note> though they be red like crimſon, they may be as wooll. <hi>God</hi> is able to bring light out of darknes, life out of death: our ſinnes ſhall turne to our good if we riſe from them more <hi>humble,</hi> more <hi>fearfull,</hi> more <hi>carefull</hi> and warie then wee were before. <hi>Happy</hi> is that fall that is taken vp by humility.<note place="margin">Bar.</note> To our <hi>repentance</hi> wee muſt adde our former good workes, from whence we are fallen: For by our good workes <hi>wee glorifie our father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. By them <hi>wee ſhew our faith Ia.</hi> 2. By them our <hi>conſciences</hi> are quieted,<note place="margin">Ia. 2.18.</note> being ſure ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to fall, <hi>making our calling and election ſure.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. Yet <hi>merit</hi> by theſe wee cannot,<note place="margin">2. Pet 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ified</hi> by them wee are not. Euery one muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15635:25"/>as <hi>Gregory, Nudum me in fide prima gratia ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit, nudum eadem gratia in aſsumptione ſaluabit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gr. Meral. l <hi>2</hi> c. <hi>40.</hi> p. <hi>11.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi> Edit. Par. <hi>1551.</hi>
               </note> the firſt grace begot in vs faith when wee were but naked in good workes, and the ſame grace ſhall ſaue vs hereafter when we ſhal be but naked in them neither. <hi>Non proecedunt iuſtificandum, ſed ſequuntur iuſtificatum,</hi> they are the ſignes of our ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not the cauſes of our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That learned ſpeech of reuerend <hi>Caluin</hi> ſhall euer be true, <hi>Fides ſola eſt quae iuſtificat, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des tamen quae iuſtificat nonest ſola. Vt ſolis calor ſolus eſt qui terram calefaciat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. in Act. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. Trid. Sext Seſſ. Antid. Tract. Theol. p. <hi>336.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non tamen idem inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſolus eſt, quia coniunctus cum ſplendore.</hi> It is faith alone that iuſtifieth, and yet <hi>that faith that iuſtifieth is not alone.</hi> As it is the heate alone of the <hi>Sunne</hi> that heateth the earth, yet is not that heat in the <hi>Sunne</hi> alone, becauſe it hath bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ioyned with it. <hi>Repentance</hi> and good workes cannot be ſeuered. Behold a Chriſtian muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, elſe he ſhall neuer taſt the ſweet <hi>Manna</hi> of comfort from aboue.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Angels</hi> of heauen need not to repent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſinne not: the <hi>Diuels</hi> in hell care not for repentance, their iudgement is ſealed, but it appertaineth to vs all who are the ſonnes of men, and muſt be practiſed if euer wee will goe to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. <hi>Our marble</hi> and flinty hearts muſt bee ſofre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the ſweet ſhowers of Gods heauenly word. <hi>Our stiffe</hi> and iron-ſinued neckes muſt bee bowed with the yoake either of the Goſpell or of the law. <hi>Our foreheads</hi> muſt not be like hers
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15635:25"/>that refuſed to bee aſhamed.<note place="margin">Math. 11.30. Act. 15.10. Ie. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Our eares</hi> muſt not be ſo deafe, <hi>our eyes</hi> ſo drye, our <hi>ſenſes</hi> ſo dull, <hi>our wills</hi> ſo obſtinate, <hi>our affections</hi> ſo barren, <hi>our deſires</hi> ſo cold, but wee muſt awake. The gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>bels</hi> of <hi>Aaron,</hi> the thundring <hi>trompets</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay,</hi> the well-tuned <hi>Cimbals</hi> of <hi>Dauid,</hi> the ſhrill <hi>ſound</hi> of preaching, aime onely at our conuerſion to God. O <hi>conſider</hi> this you that forget God. <hi>(I ſpeake only to them whoſe conſctences accuſe them)</hi> If you make <hi>religion</hi> but faſhion, ſeeking onely to ſeeme Chriſtians, hauing Gods liuery on your backes, and name in your mouthes, yet <hi>outfacing</hi> all reproofes by your <hi>inſatiable</hi> couetouſnes, <hi>biting</hi> vſury, <hi>falſe</hi> meaſures, <hi>forſworne</hi> valuations, <hi>adulterat</hi> wares, catching at the poſſeſſions of the Church, grinding and griping the faces of the poore, by which meanes, howſoeuer you fill your Coffer, you feſter your <hi>ſoules,</hi> though your <hi>faces</hi> were like <hi>Angels,</hi> without repentance and good workes there muſt follow a portion with the Diuels, from which <hi>Good Lord deliuer vs.</hi> O then while it is called <hi>to day,</hi> let vs ranſacke our hearts and get a ſound <hi>affection</hi> to God, a firme <hi>reſolution</hi> to goodnes, <hi>hatred</hi> to ſinne in all men, eſpecially in our ſelues, and an obedient <hi>keeping</hi> of the commandements. O then you whom God hath endowed with holy and vpright hearts, that haue done and intend ſtill to doe honour to your maker, honeſty to the Goſpell, credit to this famous Citie, <hi>Be ſtedfaſt and vnmoueable al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies abcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in theſe works of the Lora, knowing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15635:26"/>that your labour is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi> You are not <hi>Treaſurers</hi> but <hi>Stewards,</hi> whoſe praiſe is more to lay out well, then to haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued much. Neither the <hi>times</hi> nor your ſelues are in your owne diſpoſing, the more ſpeedily <hi>you doe good, the more comfort you ſhall receiue.</hi> O then let vs all follow <hi>Austins</hi> aduiſe,<note place="margin">Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>33.</hi> in Job.</note>, take time while time is offered, leaſt the gate of <hi>mercy</hi> which to day is open, to morrow bee ſhut and neuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened againe vnto vs. <hi>Let vs</hi> beware that wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe not the patience and long ſuffering of ſo good a God, leaſt after ſo-many calmes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, he powre downe vpon vs the bitter <hi>ſtormes</hi> of indignation and come quickly againſt vs, as hee threateneth to come againſt <hi>Epheſus;</hi> which is the firſt particular of my ſecond generall. <hi>Of elſe I willcome vnto thee quickly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prima ſecundae.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such</hi> are the neuer-ſtinting <hi>ſtreames</hi> of Gods <hi>mercy,</hi> that hee neuer ouerthroweth any King dome or nation, Citty or people, before he ſend a warning peece to admoniſh them. He endured the people of the Iewes ſufficiently in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, proteſting in the Pſalmes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 95 10.</note> 
               <hi>Forty years long was I grieued with this generation,</hi> not onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked, offended diſcontented, but <hi>grieued</hi> at his very ſoule: who could haue grieued all the veines of their hearts, and taught them the price of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring ſo dreadfull a Maieſty as his is. A <hi>genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> for whoſe ſake hee had wrought many won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, preparing a <hi>table</hi> for them in the deſart, their diet <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iles</hi> and <hi>Manna,</hi> in ſuch aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15635:26"/>in ſuch delicacie, that neuer any Prince was ſo ſerued in his greateſt pompe, hee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered them from a bondage worſe then death, vanquiſht many Kings for them, and led them by miracle through the red Sea, yet they murmure, repine, grudge, rebell; and when no fauour could moue them, God ſweareth in his wrath that they ſhould not enter into his reſt. His <hi>patience</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moued turneth into fury. <hi>Here are mercy and iudgement,</hi> that hee threateneth before hee puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth: and it is conditionall. <hi>Vpon</hi> the opening of the ayre and ſhutting of the windowes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, after the waters had ouer-run the world in 150. dayes, God ſet his bow in the cloud, a token of Couenant betwixt him and the earth: Not but that there was Raine and a Raine bow before the flood: for how elſe could the plants and fruites of the earth haue beene ſo many yeares preſerued without Raine? but Now it began to be a ſigne twixt God and man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen. 9.11.</hi> Doct. Will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t in Gen.</note> that there ſhould be no more a flood to deſtroy the earth. A <hi>ſigne</hi> ſo terrible to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euery appearing of it they come forth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their ſinnes, and dare not looke vp towards heauen. But it is an emblem of Gods mercie (ſaith <hi>Ramban</hi>) the ends turned downwards and the back to heauen, he that ſhooteth holding the back from him: or (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) it was mercie that he made the bow his token, and not the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: the <hi>Bowe</hi> is but the inſtrument, the <hi>arrowe</hi> woundeth. So dealeth he with <hi>Epheſus,</hi> his <hi>Bow</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15635:27"/>is bent, but he will not ſhoote if they repent. <hi>Elſe I will come.</hi> Many parts of mans <hi>body</hi> are aſcribed vnto God in Scripture, the <hi>face,</hi> the <hi>mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ</hi> 34.16. De. 8.3. 2. Ki. 19.16. Zac. 4.10. 1. Ki. 8.42. Mat. 22.44. <hi>De hoec. c.</hi> 50.</note> the <hi>eares,</hi> the <hi>eyes,</hi> the <hi>armes,</hi> the <hi>feet:</hi> whence moſt groſly <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and ſome Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, who by <hi>Epiphanius</hi> are called <hi>Audiani,</hi> and by <hi>Auguſtine, Vadiani:</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptian Monkes</hi> the <hi>Anthropomorphitae</hi> collected that <hi>God</hi> was a body: an error ſo abſurd, that the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of it are rather to be <hi>puniſhed then anſwered.</hi> For it is a true <hi>axiome</hi> in ſchoole-Diuinity, that <hi>Quaecunque de Deo corporaliter dicuntur, dicta ſunt ſymbolice,</hi> Whatſoeuer is ſpoken of God bodily, muſt be vnderſtood figuratiuely. It is the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of the ſpirit to fit the ſcriptures to our weake capacities, to vſe known familiar and ſenſible tearmes, thereby to raiſe vp our conceits to ſome knowledge of the euerliuing God. His <hi>comming</hi> ſignifieth his <hi>readineſſe. Behold</hi> ſayth <hi>Salomon, He commeth leaping vpon the mountaines, skipping vpon the hils, like a Roe or a young Hart. ca.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ca.</hi> 2.8.9.</note> 2. His comming is either for <hi>mercy,</hi> as to <hi>Adam</hi> with the promiſe in time of deſpaire; to <hi>Abraham</hi> with ſupply in time of ſacrifice;<note place="margin">Ge. 3.8 15. Ge. 22.13. Ge. 26 2.3. Ge 41.40. 1. Ki. 19.5. Iu 6.21.</note>to <hi>Izaac</hi> with reliefe in time of famine; to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> with honour in time of exile; to <hi>Eliah</hi> with comfort in time of perſecution; to <hi>Gedeon</hi> with a ſtaff in time of battaile; to <hi>Ezechia</hi> with triumph in time of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſion; to <hi>Daniel</hi> among the Lions; to the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> in the furnace; to <hi>Suſanna</hi> at the place of iudgement; to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the iayle; to the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15635:27"/>
               <hi>Theefe</hi> vpon the croſſe. <hi>Veniens ventet,</hi> Hee ſhall come quickly when hee commeth to deliuer; <hi>or hee commeth</hi> in iudgement ſpeedily and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: It is long ere hee <hi>reuenge</hi> himſelfe vpon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but when hee commeth <hi>his hands be of iron,</hi> hee payeth home and with a witneſſe. <hi>If a man turne not, hee will whet his ſword:</hi> hee hath bent his bow and made it ready,<note place="margin">Pſ. 7.13.13.</note> hee hath alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for him the inſtruments of death: hee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth his arrowes and theſe ſly ſwiftly. God commeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, quickly; which leadeth vs to this <hi>collection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct. That Gods iudgments come ſpeedily vpon the impenitent and obſtinate.</hi> The <hi>reaſon</hi> is giuen <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. <hi>My ſpirit ſhall not alwaies ſtriue with man,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.3. <hi>Olcaſter.</hi>
               </note> hee would no longer reproue and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them, ſeeing they reguarded it not; <hi>or</hi> hee would no longer <hi>conſult</hi> and diſpute the matter as it were with himſelfe what to doe with them, but if they amended not within the ſpace giuen them to repent,<note place="margin">Iunius.</note> he would ſuddainly deſtroy them; and ſo he did. <hi>One</hi> poore family was called out of a world, and as it were eight graines of corne fanned from a whole barne full of chaffe; the reſt were drowned. <hi>How</hi> ſpeedily and quickly was he reuenged vpon <hi>Lots</hi> wife, turning her into a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Salt! <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. A ſuddaine <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> or ſtrange <hi>transformation</hi> of a miſerable and ſinfull woman,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.26.</note> for but a glaunce of her eye: ſhe goeth forward and looketh backward, as if her neck had beene broke when ſhee was brought out of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15635:28"/>from that kindred and country where ſhe had liued, from her houſe where ſhe had dwelt, from her gardens, pleaſure, ſweet ayre, greene paſtures and pleaſant waters, which ſhee had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed. <hi>O what a bewitching is it to the ſoule of man to fall in loue with the fleſhpots of Aegypt! Poore woman</hi> ſhe had particular warning of the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Sodome, which, her houſe and kinred excepted, none in Sodome had beſide her. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> ſometimes ſtood with a ſword to keepe men out of Paradiſe,<note place="margin">M. Wilkinſon in his ſermon vpon Lots Wife.</note> but theſe who were appoynted to deſtroy Sodome bring peace to her, and bring her out of Sodome. <hi>Angels</hi> appeared to her, not as to <hi>Iacob</hi> in a ladder, nor as to <hi>Moſes</hi> in a buſh, nor as to <hi>Samuel</hi> in the Tabernacle, but they came into her houſe. <hi>She</hi> had leaue to carry her goods with her. <hi>She</hi> was pardoned one delay before, an Angel laying hold vpon her hand. <hi>She</hi> was charged not to looke behind her, yet ſhe did: and therefore for her <hi>diſobedience</hi> vnto this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, her <hi>incredulity</hi> not giuing credit to Gods word, her <hi>curioſity</hi> in deſiring to ſee the citty bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, her <hi>folly</hi> in pittying thoſe that would not pitty their owne ſoules, her <hi>affection</hi> to that place which was lothſome to God, ſhee was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turned into a pillar of Salt, <hi>vt praeſtet fidelibus condimentum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An: l. <hi>16.</hi> deciu. Dei. c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> noteth; that it may be a ſeaſoning to faithfull men to take heede of backſliding. Thus the Lord puniſhed her body, though in charity wee muſt thinke he had mercy vpon her ſoule. I appeale vnto our owne daylie
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15635:28"/>experience, Whether many who led the <hi>dance</hi> in the <hi>morning</hi> haue not fallen foule, and beene blaſted in the euening.</p>
            <q>Quem vidit dies veniens ſuperbum:<note place="margin">Sen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> hunc vidit dies ſugiens iacentem.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſang this ſong, Is not this layd vp in <hi>ſtore</hi> with me, and ſealed vp among my treaſures? <hi>To me belongeth vengance and recompence, their foote ſhall ſlide in due time:</hi> for the day of their calamity is at hand, and the things that ſhall come vpon them make haſt.<note place="margin">De 32.35.</note> 
               <hi>Deu.</hi> 32. Thus <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel</hi> threateneth <hi>Ieruſalem, Thoa art betome guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the blood which thou haſt ſhed, and haſt defiled thy ſelfe in thine Idols which thou haſt made; and thou haſt cauſed thy daies to draw neere, and art come euen vnto thine yeares, therefore haue I made thee a reproch vnto the heathhen, and a mocking to all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. Eze.</hi> 22. <hi>Thus Saint</hi> Iohn <hi>threatneth</hi> Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.<note place="margin">Ez. 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>I will come vnto thee quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which</hi> may ſerue as a <hi>terrour</hi> vnto all lingring and irreſolute Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> that put a farre off the day for wrath from them, crying out as thoſe <hi>ſcoffers</hi> which walke after their owne luſts, and ſaying, where is the promiſe of his comming? For ſince the Fathers fel aſleep, al thinges conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new as they were from the beginning of the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. 2 <hi>Pe.</hi> 3. Like that euill <hi>ſeruant</hi> which ſaid in his heart, My Lord delayeth his comming,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.4.</note> and therfore ſmiteth his fellow ſeruant, eating and drinking with the drunken.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.48.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. <hi>O did the oppreſsor,</hi> that <hi>Miſanthropos,</hi> that <hi>Sarcophagus,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15635:29"/>Anthropophagus, Anthropomaſtix,</hi> the <hi>hater, whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> &amp; <hi>eater</hi> of men, which with the ſharpnes of his talents gripeth his <hi>tenants</hi> with miſerable <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion;</hi> and in his contracts plucking out the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hearts of his creditors by an execrable <hi>defal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of their debtes, eateth them vp like bread. <hi>But remember</hi> that the Lord is comming vnto him <hi>quickly:</hi> then ſhould not the poore mans <hi>pledge</hi> be wrongfully witholden, the labourers <hi>hire</hi> kept back till the morning, ſo many <hi>buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> be enlarged by <hi>Ahabs</hi> cruelty, ſo many <hi>coffers</hi> enriched by <hi>Iudas</hi> trechery, ſo many <hi>ſhops</hi> ſorted with wares, ſo many <hi>warehouſes</hi> with ſtore, ſo many <hi>tables</hi> with dainties, ſo many <hi>Cubbards</hi> with plate, ſo many <hi>wardrobes</hi> with ſuits, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>granaries</hi> with corne by <hi>biting vſury:</hi> then would he not walke as <hi>Leuiathan</hi> in the Sea with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a hooke in his noſtrils, as <hi>Behemoth</hi> in the wildernes hauing no bridle in his iawes, as a ramping and roaring <hi>Lyon</hi> ſeeking whom hee may deuoure. I am ſure <hi>goods</hi> ſo gotten ſhall be but as a broken ſtaffe of reed: if a man leane, it wil pearce into his hands. Such <hi>pleaſures</hi> are but as <hi>Dalilah</hi> to <hi>Sampſon, giues</hi> and fetters of Sathan to entangle them: ſuch <hi>gold</hi> will be a <hi>milstone</hi> about their necks, to carry them into the bottomleſſe pit: ſuch <hi>lands</hi> and goods, as a bunch vpon a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels backe, not ſuffring them to enter into the narrow gate which leadeth to Ieruſalem, vnles they quickly repent. <hi>O did the Glutton</hi> remember that God is able to come <hi>quickly</hi> againſt him, he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15635:29"/>would not make his <hi>Church</hi> his <hi>Kitchin; gurmun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing</hi> his <hi>Chamberlain;</hi> his <hi>table,</hi> his <hi>altar;</hi> his <hi>Cooke,</hi> his <hi>Preacher;</hi> the <hi>O dours</hi> of his meate, his <hi>ſacrifice; ſwearing,</hi> his <hi>prayer; quaffing,</hi> his <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> &amp; his <hi>whole life, wanton fare. O did the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard</hi> but remember this that God is ready to come <hi>quickly</hi> againſt him, hee would not riſe early to follow ſtrong drinkes, which trouble the <hi>head, ouerthrow</hi> the ſenſes, cauſe the <hi>feete</hi> to reele, <hi>tongue</hi> to ſtammer, <hi>eyes</hi> to roule, and the whole <hi>fabrick</hi> of his little world to be poſſeſſed with this <hi>voluntary madnes, loſſe of money, friends, credit, time;</hi> This ſweet poyſon and flattering Diuell. <hi>What</hi> ſhall I ſay more? I muſt proceed, for I haue more vices to taxe, and the time run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. It is like a riuer,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nec enim conſistere flumen,</l>
               <l>Nec leuis hora poteſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wee haue as much need to be terrified, as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus:</hi> our ſinnes are the like. I <hi>confeſſe</hi> they are not expreſſed in my <hi>Text,</hi> but elſwhere ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that hee that runneth by the paſſages of holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> may read them largely deſcribed. <hi>Epheſus</hi> had many <hi>backſliders</hi> in Religion, reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Apoſtataes: haue not wee the like?</hi> It would make a man <hi>amazed</hi> and aſhamed, to ſee the <hi>zeale</hi> of the firſt Chriſtians, and our coldnes; to look vpon the <hi>valiant</hi> onſet of our <hi>heroical</hi> reformers, and the flagging ſeconding them in theſe dayes. The people of <hi>Samoſatum</hi> would not come into the Church when their good Biſhop <hi>Euſebius</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:15635:30"/>was deptiued,<note place="margin">Theod. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Eunomius</hi> an hereticall Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op thruſt into his place by the <hi>Arrians: None of the inhahitants eithir poore or rich, huſbandman or grafter, man or woman, young or old</hi> (ſaith <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret</hi>) <hi>would come to the Church, either to ſee him or confer with him.</hi> But how many are there now that will come to no <hi>Sermon,</hi> vnles the Preacher be ſome <hi>mongril temporiſer,</hi> too forward to ſnarle at thoſe bleſſed worthies, <hi>Caluin, Beza, Luther &amp;c.</hi> Better it were for our Church, if theſe <hi>giddy cenſurers</hi> were open <hi>Heretiques. Auſt in</hi> thought it a ſcandall to heare a <hi>Donatiſt</hi> ſpeake,<note place="margin">L. de paſto. c. 7.</note> and hee to hold his peace, leaſt the hearer ſhould take falſhood to be truth. But how many ſeeming <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are there, that by their ſilence encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage railing <hi>Rabſhakees black mouthed</hi> followers of the Romiſh ſectto diſgorge lothſome contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melies againſt our <hi>Religion, Soueraigne, and whole eſtate?</hi> oftentimes ſpeaking <hi>blaſphemies, ex deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata malitia contra conſcientiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aq.</note> vpon prepenſed malice againſt their owne knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. <hi>Iohn</hi> would not be in the ſame bath with <hi>Cerinthus; Polycarpus</hi> would not ſalute <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſ. biſt. <hi>1.22.</hi> l. <hi>4.13.</hi> Theod. hiſt. eel. l. <hi>4.14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Antiochus</hi> would not ſuffer <hi>Iouianus</hi> to touch him becauſe he was an <hi>Arrian:</hi> Our owne <hi>Ridley</hi> comming to the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> offering to preach and being reuſed, yet entertained by ſome <hi>religious Courtier</hi> to <hi>diner;</hi> after hee had drunke, looking ſadly, he cryed out <hi>I haue done amiſſe to drinke in that place where Gods word offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hath bene refuſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fox. p. <hi>1270.</hi> Anno <hi>1553.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>whereas if I had remembred
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15635:30"/>my duty, I ought to haue departed immediately, and haue ſhaken the dust off my ſhooes for a teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this houſe.</hi> But what is more common now then for the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of God to match with the daughters of men, and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with <hi>Papiſts, who can neuer be true to vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo falſe to God and their Prince? Compariſons</hi> would proue odious if they were further proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuted, as they might be: yet let me adde ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe. <hi>Epheſus</hi> had many who addicted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to ſpels and charmes and knots, called <hi>Epheſiae literae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suidas in exico. Philoſtratus l. <hi>4.</hi> Eustathius in odyſs.</note> inſomuch that one <hi>Mileſius</hi> at the Olympian games by the help of theſe conquered 30. of their valiant'ſt men, but when theſe Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries were taken from him,<note place="margin">Plut. in Symp. l. <hi>7.</hi> q. <hi>5.</hi> athenaeus l. <hi>XI.</hi> Bud. de aſſe. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> hee fainted. Their books of theſe curious arts were worth 50000. peices of ſiluer. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.19. that is 5000. crowns as <hi>Budaeus</hi> accounteth. Haue there beene none a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs ſo that there were not more remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but <hi>ſome mens ſinnes are open before hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ti. 5.24.25.</note> 
               <hi>going before to iudgement, and they who are yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed cannot be hid that</hi> wit <hi>Saul</hi> forſake the true Prophets,<note place="margin">1 Sa. 28.7.</note> and runne to ſome <hi>Woman</hi> that hath a familiar <hi>ſpirit; that</hi> with <hi>Ahaziah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kit 1.2.</note> for a fall ſend to <hi>Baalzebub</hi> the God of <hi>Ekron,</hi> to enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhall recouer of this diſeaſe. And it falleth out with them according to the Spaniſh Prouerbe, <hi>from long iourneyes large lyes are affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> The <hi>Iewes</hi> could reaſon thus.<note place="margin">Da luengas vias luengas menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas.</note> He hath a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, why heare yee him? (a damnable aſperſion put vpon <hi>Chriſt</hi>) but theſe will harken vnto none<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.20.</note>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:15635:31"/>ſo much as to them who haue Deuils. And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Philoſophie</hi> teacheth that <hi>nothing can bee in intellectu, which hath not firſt been drawn by fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie from common ſenſe,</hi> yet theſe hold That future things which neuer came within the ſenſe, may be compriſed in the vnderſtanding. Yea though an <hi>Angel</hi> could not tell <hi>Eſdras</hi> how long hee ſhould liue.<note place="margin">2. Eſd. 4 52.</note> 2. <hi>Eſd</hi> yet theſe will profeſſe to put a period vnto our liues, when our dayes are deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, our monthes numbred, our bounds ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed which wee cannot paſſe, onely in Gods hand.<note place="margin">Iob. 14.5.</note> 
               <hi>Iob.</hi> 14. So <hi>deteſtable</hi> were theſe to the old Chriſtians that they were adorned with this title <hi>Incantamentorum oppugnatores,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> oppugners of all kinds of ſorcerie; as the Kings and Queenes of our realmes are called <hi>Defendors</hi> of the faith. I leaue our <hi>Starre-gazers,</hi> which ſeem to find vnder the <hi>Moone</hi> vnconſtant friends; vnder <hi>Mercury,</hi> chaſt men borne; vnder <hi>Venus,</hi> luſtfull wantons; vnder <hi>Sol,</hi> honourable preferments; vnder <hi>Mars,</hi> valiant Soldiers; vnder <hi>Iupiter</hi> quick-ſpirited ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; vnder <hi>Saturne,</hi> ſober and Charitable Cenſurers.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Meditation</hi> which made <hi>Auſtin</hi> commend his friend <hi>Firminus</hi> for leauing this ſtudy, as a ſpoyle of time and ſchoole of vanity; when two children were born in the ſame moment vnder one roofe,<note place="margin">Aug Conf. l. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> and yet ſo much difference to bee betwixt them, that the one was by a cuſtome of the Country to bee ſlaue to the other. And <hi>Clement</hi> inueighed bitterly againſt thoſe,<note place="margin">Clemens. recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. l. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> which aſcribed to <hi>Andro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meda</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:15635:31"/>baniſhment, to <hi>Orion</hi> an influence of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to <hi>Canopus</hi> a deſire to fiſh, to <hi>Meduſas</hi> ſtarre ſudden death, &amp;c. But I remember <hi>Tertullians</hi> opinion, <hi>De Aſtrologis ne loguendum quidem eſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. q. <hi>11.</hi> c. Sed &amp; illud.</note> That wee ſhould not ſo much as ſpeake of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers;</hi> becauſe they honour Idols; regiſtring their names in heauen, <hi>Mars, Iupiter, Venus, Saturne;</hi> becauſe they ſeeke to tye vs to the courſe of the Planets, and leaue Gods prouidence; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their grounds were inuented by the Diuel: and therefore ſaith hee, <hi>eadem poena exitii &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipulis &amp; Magiſtris,</hi> there is one penalty of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction prouided both for the ſchollers and the Maſters; to be excluded out of heauen. I <hi>pitty</hi> ſuch, as <hi>Cambiſes</hi> did himſelfe,<note place="margin">Euſe. in Ora. Conſt. adſancta. c: <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> of whom <hi>Euſebius</hi> teſtifieth, <hi>Cambiſen poenituit malcuolis, Magorum vocibus tam facilè fuiſſe perſuaſum,</hi> Hee repented that hee had ſuffered himſelfe ſo eaſily to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by theſe ſeducers. <hi>Vpon Repentance ſuch haue been forgiuen, and ſuffered with much compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the iudgement of the lawes.</hi> I looke back vpon <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epheſus</hi> had many contemners of the Apoſtles, men ſpeaking peruerſe thinges to draw diſciples after them.<note place="margin">Act 20.30. 1. Co. 16.9.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 20. <hi>We</hi> haue many who quench the <hi>Spirit</hi> by deſpiſing our Prophets: yet a <hi>Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> is left amongſt vs, as in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> who are as vnwilling to leaue their zealous Paſtors, as the <hi>Epheſians</hi> were to leaue Saint <hi>Paul;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.25.37.</note> who when he had told them, <hi>Ye ſhall ſee my face no more,</hi> they all <hi>wept ſore, and fell on his neck and kiſsed him. Hee</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:15635:32"/>had warned euery one of them night and day with <hi>teares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 31.</note> by the ſpace of <hi>three yeares,</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſhed teares at his departure. <hi>Many</hi> ſuch <hi>Prophets</hi> and men of God are amongſt vs, who with <hi>praying, preaching, weeping and watching,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to doe the workes of <hi>Euangeliſts,</hi> and to prepare vs quickly for the Lord, leaſt hee come vpon vs as he threatned to come vnto <hi>Epheſus. Elſe I will come vnto thee quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Leſſon</hi> for our <hi>inſtruction,</hi> to admoniſh vs quickly to repent.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2.</note> For delay breedeth danger, one ſinne tolleth on another. If wee are not fit to day, wee ſhall be leſſe fit to morrow the <hi>cuſtome</hi> of ſinning ſhall take way the ſenſe of ſinne, and our offences will goe ouer our heads, a burthen too heauy for vs to beare, without ſpeedy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion. Alas can that worke be effected ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which requireth <hi>carefulnes, cleering of our ſelues, indignation, feare, vehement deſire, zeale and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge.</hi> 2. <hi>Co.</hi> 7. <hi>renewed and reformed affections?</hi> It is not enough to repent for groſſe ſinnes,<note place="margin">2. Co. 7.11.</note> 
               <hi>adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, theft, drunkenneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> but wee muſt repent for the want of grace as of the <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>feare of God,</hi> of <hi>brotherly loue,</hi> and the decay of any grace bee it neuer ſo little. <hi>I charge thee therefore, (bleſſed Chriſtian) before God and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt who ſhall iudge the quick and the dead at his appearing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Ti. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>and Kingdome, Bee not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, God is not mocked. Remember what good moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, deſires, affections and actions were in thee, and if thou decay recouer thy loſse, do the firſt works quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:15635:32"/>
I <hi>appeale</hi> vnto thine owne ſoule, whether thou haſt not had ſometimes a purpoſe to repent, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others liue <hi>religiouſly,</hi> and dye <hi>peaceably,</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſo many calles, <hi>taſting</hi> ſo many mercies of God. What letteth at this inſtant but that this courſe ſhould bee taken, to reſolue as <hi>Dauid, I made haſt, and prolonged not the time,</hi> I delayed not to keep thy commandements.<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.60.</note> 
               <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119. to doe as <hi>Peter,</hi> as ſoon as the Cock crew, hee went out and <hi>wept bitterly. Mat.</hi> 26. <hi>Then</hi> wee ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the <hi>euill day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.75.</note> which ſuddainely may elſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertake vs. <hi>Then</hi> wee ſhould haue our <hi>lamps</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whenſoeuer the Bridegroome paſſeth by vs: <hi>then</hi> wee ſhould bee furniſhed with <hi>wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> when the maiſter of the feaſt commeth to take notice of vs. <hi>God</hi> commands this, <hi>Reaſon</hi> directeth to it, and therefore wee muſt doe it: for to ſay wee cannot, is childiſh, and we will not is peeuiſh.<note place="margin">Sen. conſol. ad Polyb. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Shall Seneca</hi> call our whole life a <hi>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> and wee beſtow no time in repentance? <hi>Shall</hi> that teſtimony bee giuen of vs which <hi>Lact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antius</hi> gaue of Greece: There was neuer leſſe <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> then in the time of the 7. wiſemen? Neuer more <hi>Preaching</hi> and leſſe practiſing.<note place="margin">Vide Plin. l. <hi>30.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Shall wee be ready to receaue ſo many groſſe <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines,</hi> bitter <hi>pills,</hi> violent <hi>potions,</hi> cuttings,<note place="margin">Galen l. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizings &amp; launcings of the fleſh, to be freed from a bodily diſeaſe,<note place="margin">Paul. Aegin. l. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> and vſe no helps to be eaſed of our <hi>foule</hi> ſinnes? The <hi>Heathen</hi> could tell vs,<note place="margin">Epiour. apud. Laertium.</note> that no man was too old to learne thoſe things which concerned the health of the minde. <hi>Come</hi> hither
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15635:33"/>therefore if thou labour and art heauy loaden vnder the burthen of thy ſinne. <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> out of his graue, after hee had laine ſo long that hee ſtunke,<note place="margin">Iohn 11.39.</note> and therefore can raiſe vs out of the graue of <hi>ſin,</hi> though wee ſeeme paſt recouery.<note place="margin">Tertull. de pae. c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>God would not threaten him that doth not repent, if he would not pardon him that doth repent.</hi> The firſt degree of <hi>happineſse</hi> is not to ſin,<note place="margin">Cyp. Ep. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> (a thing which no man can chalenge) but the ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree is to confeſſe our ſinnes and bee ſorry for them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 55.7.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>O then</hi> let the wicked forſake his way, and the vnrighteous man his thoughts, and let him returne vnto the Lord, and hee will haue mercy vpon him, <hi>and to our God</hi> for hee will aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pardon. His <hi>thoughts</hi> are not our thoughts: for as the heauens are higher then the earth, ſo are his wayes higher then our waies. <hi>Deſpaire not:</hi> Our ſinnes may be meaſured and numbred;<note place="margin">Baſ. reg. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. quaeſt. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> but it is impoſſible that Gods goodneſſe ſhould bee meaſured, or his mercies numbred. <hi>Deſpaire for ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Mor. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>is worſe then ſinne it ſelfe.</hi> But let our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion bee ſpeedy. True <hi>Repentance</hi> can neuer be too late, yet late repentance is ſeldome true. We read but of one that repented at the laſt,<note place="margin">Aug</note> that no man ſhould preſume: and yet of <hi>one</hi> that none ſhould deſpaire. O then before the <hi>pearle</hi> be taken out of our field; before the ſound of the Goſpel bee remooued out of our land; before the Arke of God bee taken from vs,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4 11.</note> as it was from the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites: let vs be moued to awake vp our firſt loue quickly. Gods mercy and iudgements, and word;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15635:33"/>the <hi>infiniteneſſe</hi> of our ſinnes, <hi>ſhortneſse</hi> of our life, ſmall number of thoſe that ſhall bee ſaued, <hi>ioyes</hi> of heauen and <hi>torments</hi> of hell; are motiues: and if theſe preuaile not, our Church muſt fall as it is threatened to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> in Gods viſitation, <hi>And wil remoue thy Candleſtick out of his place, except thou repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of God is compared to many things in holy Scripture,<note place="margin">ſecunda ſecundae</note> to a <hi>houſe</hi> 1. <hi>Ti.</hi> 3. to a <hi>Body Ep.</hi> 1. to a <hi>field, Mat.</hi> 13. to a <hi>net,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ti. 3.15. Ep. 1.23. Mat 13.24. v. 47. Mat. 25.1.</note> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 47. to ten <hi>Virgins, Mat.</hi> 25. and heere to a <hi>Candleſtick.</hi> So it is expounded in 20. v. c. 1. The ſeauen <hi>Candleſtickes</hi> which thou ſaweſt are the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Churches.</hi> God threatning to remoue the Church. A <hi>fearefull iudgement,</hi> whether we take it concerning the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> that hee ſhould bee depriued of his calling, as the Lord threateneth vnto <hi>Ieremy,</hi> If thou returne I will bring thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and thou ſhalt ſtand before me: giuing him to vnderſtand when hee had been wanting in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering the Lords will vnto his people, partly through feare, and partly through impatience, that if hee returned not, he ſhould ceaſe to be a Prophet vnto him. Or if wee take it for the whole <hi>body</hi> of a Church, that they ſhould procure the remouing of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> from them, and the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the <hi>Goſpell:</hi> or if wee take it as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth euery priuate man,<note place="margin">Commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iones et promiſſines diuae ſunt hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticae. <hi>33,</hi> mor. c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> that he ſhall loſe the knowledge of God and other graces. <hi>It is condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall, Except thou repent.</hi> Thus, as <hi>Gregory</hi> noteth, <hi>Vt pius, it a iuſtus eſt Conditor:</hi> As our Maker is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15635:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>mercifull, ſo is hee iuſt, <hi>Gracious and righteous.</hi> Good and vpright is the Lord to teach ſinners in the way.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 25.8.</note> 
               <hi>Pſ.</hi> 25. <hi>Good and gracious</hi> in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his mercies to them that turne vnto him: <hi>Righteous and vpright</hi> in the ſeuerity of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to them that caſt him from them. Heere are <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>wrath, pitty</hi> and <hi>reuenge,</hi> two Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of a great King goe hand in hand: If the one cannot draw, the other muſt, the Church ſhall be remoued, the light of the Goſpell ſhall bee put out; For as the <hi>Candleſtick</hi> holdeth the light, ſo doth the Church the word: without this wee walke in darkenes and obſcurity: ſo that here I muſt land and faſten vpon this note,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>That the taking away of the Miniſtry and preaching of the word is the greateſt plague that can befall any.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>reaſons</hi> are well knowne. Where there is no <hi>viſion</hi> the people periſh.<note place="margin">Pro. 29.18. 2. Ch. 15.3. Ro. 10.17.</note> 
               <hi>Pro.</hi> 29. Where there is not a teaching Prieſt, and law, there is no <hi>God.</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 15. <hi>Faith</hi> commeth by hearing. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. ſo that <hi>take</hi> away the word, and <hi>take</hi> away faith; <hi>take</hi> away faith, <hi>take</hi> away <hi>Chriſt; take</hi> away <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>take</hi> away eternall life. Therefore vpon <hi>Aarons</hi> robe there were <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Bells,</hi> ſignifying the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; and <hi>Pomegranates,</hi> ſignifying the ſweete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of <hi>Christs</hi> death.<note place="margin">Exo 28.34.</note> 
               <hi>Ex.</hi> 28. The <hi>miſeries</hi> which follow this are vnſpeakeable: To be <hi>blind</hi> and haue no guide, and yet to walke there where treading awry is the tumbling into hell: to be <hi>hungry,</hi> and to famiſh: to <hi>ſuck,</hi> but on dry breſts:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15635:34"/>to be <hi>pined,</hi> and not perceiue it, which is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill of euills. Therefore was <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> threatned, that their prophets tongue ſhould cleaue to the roofe of his mouth, &amp; he ſhould be dumbe, and not be vnto them a reprouer. <hi>Ez.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Ez. 3.26.</note> and this fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſentence was vrged from the mouth of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe. I ſay vnto you, the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of God ſhall be taken from you, and giuen to a Nation bringing forth the fruits thereof. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.<note place="margin">Mat. 21.43.</note> And if this <hi>kingdome</hi> be once gone, their ioy goeth with it: All the <hi>Empires</hi> and <hi>dominions</hi> in the world ſubdued, all <hi>Scepters</hi> and <hi>Crownes</hi> heaped together cannot bleſſe them. A greater iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then any <hi>inuaſion</hi> of enemies; then <hi>firing</hi> of townes, ruinating of houſes, <hi>rauiſhing</hi> of wiues and daughters, <hi>daſhing</hi> of Infants againſt the ſtones in the ſtreetes, <hi>pulling</hi> out the eyes from the heads, and bowels from the bodyes of a people. <hi>Therefore</hi> the beſt haue euer dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpected Gods Ambaſſadours, the Paſtours of the Church, and the Miniſters of the word. Thus did they in the old law; <hi>Iehoiada a Prieſt, marrying Iehoſhabeath the daughter of King Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, the ſiſter of King Ahaziah</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.<note place="margin">2 Ch. 22 11.</note> Thus <hi>Ioaſh</hi> the King of Iſraell came downe in perſon to viſit ſick <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and wept ouer his face, ſaying, <hi>O my father, my father, the Chariot of Iſraell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Ki. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>and the horſmer thereof.</hi> 2 <hi>Ki.</hi> 13. In the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wee find many <hi>Poſſeſſors</hi> of lands and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſelling them, and laying downe the prices of them at the Apoſtles feete. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Act. 4.34.35</note> The hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15635:35"/>
               <hi>Treaſurer of Ethiopia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.31. Act. 10.25. Act. 17.4. Gal. 4.14.</note> taking <hi>Philip</hi> vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Chariot. <hi>Ac.</hi> 8. <hi>Cornetius</hi> a deuout liberall <hi>Martialiſt,</hi> falling downe at the <hi>feet</hi> of <hi>Peter. Aect.</hi> 10. The chiefe <hi>women</hi> in <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> conſorting with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas. Ac.</hi> 17. The <hi>Galathians</hi> receiuing S. <hi>Paul</hi> as an <hi>Angell</hi> of God, euen as <hi>Chriſt Ieſus. Gal.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries abound in examples of <hi>Valentinian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr in obitu. Valentin.</note> ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerencing <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that ſeeing him in his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes come vnto him, <hi>ſalutem ſibi quandam ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram arbitrabatur,</hi> he thought he ſaw health it ſelf comming vnto him; of <hi>Alexander</hi> lighting from his horſe, and <hi>bowing</hi> to <hi>Iaddus;</hi> of good <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> ſending for <hi>Meletius</hi> to kiſſe his lippes and embrace him:<note place="margin">Theod. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> kiſſing that eye of <hi>Paphnutius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ff</hi> 1.4.</note> a Biſhop of <hi>Thebes,</hi> which had loft light by the violence of the <hi>Arrians:</hi> of that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Earle Terentius,</hi> who hauing obtained a great victory, and being bidden of the <hi>Emperour Conſtantius</hi> to aſke what he would, <hi>Templum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiit pro orthodoxis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod. l. <hi>4.</hi> c <hi>3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> he asked to haue the Church reſtored to the orthodoxall teachers. I omit how much others haue beene honoured, <hi>Hilarius at Arles, Paulinus at Nola, Cyrill at Alexandria, Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom at Conſtantinople,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in Demo.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine at Happo, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe at Millan, Cyprian at Carthage:</hi> For if the <hi>Oratours</hi> are once yeelded, <hi>Athens</hi> muſt ſoone to wracke:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zac.</hi> 13.7.</note> if the <hi>Shepheard</hi> be ſmitten, the <hi>Sheepe</hi> will be ſcattered: if <hi>preaching,</hi> and the <hi>Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke</hi> of a place, which is the Church, bee remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, mens ſoules will runne to ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:15635:35"/>
The 1. <hi>Vſe</hi> is to taxe the <hi>Papiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. Mat. 5.15</note> who hideth this <hi>candleſtick</hi> and <hi>candle</hi> vnder a buſhell, that it cannot giue light to them that are in the houſe; ſetting lock and key vpon the Scriptures, that the laity may not come in, marking them with a <hi>Noli me tangere;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hard. act.</hi> 15. <hi>ſect</hi> 6. Mat. 7.6 Ioh. 7.49</note> calling the Comonalty <hi>Swine,</hi> and a rude people, as the <hi>Phariſes</hi> in their pride keeping their followers from the knowledge of the law, calling them curſed. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7. And as the <hi>Spartans</hi> enacted, that none ſhould walke by night with <hi>Lanthorne, Torch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. Lycur.</note> or any <hi>light,</hi> ſo haue they forbidden this which is a <hi>lampe</hi> vnto the feet, and a <hi>light</hi> vnto the path,<note place="margin">Pſal 119.105</note> leaſt the peoples vnderſtanding might proue the diſcouerie of thoſe errors, wherewith before they were by their own ignorance <hi>mizled,</hi> or by their blinde guides <hi>miſſe-led.</hi> I appeale to ancient cuſtomes.<note place="margin">Soc. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>33</hi>
               </note> Why then did <hi>Vlphilas Biſhop</hi> tranſlate the Scriptures into the <hi>Gottiſh</hi> tongue, that the <hi>Barbarians</hi> might learne them? S. <hi>Ierom</hi> into the <hi>Sclauonian</hi> language?<note place="margin">Hoſ &amp; Alpho.</note> S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> into the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menian?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> Athen. inſynop.</note> Why did <hi>Origen</hi> labour ſo much in his <hi>Exaplus?</hi> not to ſearch thoſe of <hi>Aquila, Symma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus, Theodetion,</hi> and <hi>Eucian</hi> a Martyr? Why did S. <hi>Auſten</hi> commend this, the tranſlation from one tongue into diuers languages as a guide vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſaluation? why did <hi>Macrina, Baſils</hi> nurſe,<note place="margin">Auguſt, de doct. chr, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> Baſ. op. <hi>74. Ier. epit. Paulae</hi>
               </note> teach him the Scripture of a child? <hi>Paula</hi> ſet her Maids to read the Scriptures? Why did S. <hi>Iohn</hi> dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate his ſecond Epiſtle to the elect Lady? It were impious to thinke that he would ſend her a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15635:36"/>which ſhe might not read. I leaue that other <hi>error</hi> of Rome, preferring the Church before the Scrioture: wheras the Word is the Candle, and the Church but the Candleſtick; yet if this be remoued, curſes muſt follow. From the <hi>theefe</hi> in the Candle, the <hi>Papist,</hi> I muſt come to the theefe which would take away our Candleſtick, the honours and endowments of our Church: cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out,</p>
            <q>Dicite Pontifices, in templo quid facit aurum?</q>
            <p>What ſhould the Church doe with gold?<note place="margin">Perſius.</note> In the time of <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> when the <hi>Paſtours</hi> had conſpired either not to preach at all vnto their charges, or if they did bring any thing it was <hi>poyſon</hi> for meat, and <hi>venome</hi> in ſteade of water: <hi>when Antichriſt,</hi> with his Pompe, and his <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers</hi> with the brightnes of earthly and carnall glory, had daſeled the peoples eyes that they could not ſee truth from error: <hi>when</hi> the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the <hi>tongues,</hi> and almoſt all other litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was raked vp vnder the aſhes: <hi>when</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>canons</hi> of <hi>councels,</hi> and <hi>cust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes</hi> and <hi>traditions</hi> were in place of the written word: <hi>when</hi> ſome <hi>ſchoolemen</hi> had conſpurcated and abuſed true diuinity with their filthines: <hi>when</hi> a liuely faith and vnderſtanding knowledg were not heard of; it was thought the glory and <hi>merit</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to inrich and endowe the Church: wherein howſoeuer they offended, yet (as the Moraliſt hath it) it was on the ſafer part, being in exceſſe in making the Church exceed in riches. And certainly their exceſſe in the day
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15635:36"/>of iudgment ſhall condemne the defect of many temple-Pirats, and Church-robbers, who pare and loppe the temporall eſtates of the Church: but <hi>ſuch ſtollen waters ſhall be vnto them like Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles feathers, to eat &amp; conſume the rest of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pli. l. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Aul. Gel. l. <hi>30.</hi> c <hi>9</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>like Equus Seianus, and aurum Toloſsanum,</hi> which were ſtill infortunate to thoſe that had them. O now <hi>miſerable times,</hi> wherin the <hi>Ship</hi> of our Church is toſſed betwixt <hi>Scylla and Charib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, Aram before and the Philiſtimes behind: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſticall Polititians</hi> ſeeke our liuings, as the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> our liues. <hi>How many fayre portions of the Lord, which to beſtow vpon him Deuotion diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her owne deare Children, haue beene taken away from the Church!</hi> Many <hi>golden</hi> veſſels haue bene taken from the Lords table, to furniſh priuate houſes. Many great <hi>barnes</hi> haue bene filled, and bords maintained, with the <hi>tiths</hi> of the Church: Had not the <hi>Doners ius proprietatis,</hi> power to make ſuch donations? had not <hi>Princes</hi> in thoſe times <hi>ius domini,</hi> power to allow ſuch? Had not the lawes <hi>ius determinationis</hi> power to faſten theſe by their determinations? When they were taken from the Church,<note place="margin">Iſ. 34.11.13.</note> the <hi>Cormorant</hi> and the <hi>Bitterne</hi> haue poſſeſſed them, the <hi>Owle</hi> and the <hi>Rauen</hi> haue dwelt there, there haue bene the <hi>line</hi> of confuſion, and <hi>stones</hi> of emptines: <hi>Thornes, nettles,</hi> and <hi>brambles</hi> haue come vp in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes: yea the remaining <hi>reliques</hi> of thoſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walls haue beene dig'd vp with the bones of the <hi>founders.</hi> If the <hi>ſinnes</hi> of ſome haue brought
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15635:37"/>ſuch a iudgement vpon ſome Church houſes, what ſhal become of many which turne <hi>Bethel</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Beth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uen,</hi> Gods houſe into a houſe of vanity? ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the bread of Prophets &amp; Prophets Children, to maintaine their owne pompe &amp; feed their <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, haukes, hounds,</hi> &amp; much worſe creatures. <hi>This</hi> is the cauſe of ſo much ſicknes in Religion: many ſubmit neither their hearts to the doctrine, nor their liues to the diſcipline of the Church, becauſ they ſee it ſo trampled vpon. So reuerend M. <hi>Calu.</hi> confeſſed,<note place="margin">Calu. Ep. ad Cranmer Brent. ep. ad. Ioh. Schopper.</note> 
               <hi>vnum obſtaculum intelligo, quod praedae expoſiti ſunt Eccleſiae redditus, matum ſane intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile.</hi> This terrifyeth ſo many in the ſtudy of <hi>diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> cauſeth <hi>ſchooles</hi> to bee contemned, and <hi>lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> men to be diſheartned. I would to God theſe would remember <hi>Balthaſars</hi> end, who propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the veſſels of the Temple, ſaw ſuch a <hi>hand</hi> writing vpon the wall, that his countenance was changed, his <hi>thoughts</hi> troubled him, the <hi>ioynts</hi> of his loynes were looſed, his <hi>knees</hi> ſmote one againſt the other, and <hi>in that night he was ſlaine. Da.</hi> 5. or <hi>Antiochus</hi> vpon his death bed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Da.</hi> 5 6.30 1 Mac. 6.11.12 2 Mac. 3.26. <hi>Theod.</hi> l. 3. c. 11.</note> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>this</hi> to be the <hi>occaſion</hi> of al his miſery. 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 6. or <hi>Heliodorus</hi> whipt by <hi>Angels</hi> for it. 2. <hi>Mac.</hi> 3 Or <hi>Iuliau</hi> wounded to death with an arrow from heauen, for robbing Churches; or <hi>Achans</hi> ſtoning, or <hi>Iudas</hi> hanging. When I name <hi>Iudas,</hi> I muſt remember another <hi>thiefe</hi> in our <hi>Candle</hi> and <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticke,</hi> the <hi>Simoniacall Patron,</hi> which will not part with that portion which is due vnto the Sonnes of <hi>Leui,</hi> and commited vnto them,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15635:37"/>as the <hi>golden Apple</hi> was vnto <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aris,</hi> with <hi>DETVR DIGNIORI,</hi> let the worthier haue it, <hi>Valeſſe with Iudas</hi> they couenant for a price before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand; neuer regarding the <hi>excellency</hi> and <hi>aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> of a mans <hi>learning,</hi> the <hi>ſoundneſſe</hi> of his <hi>ſaith,</hi> the <hi>vprightneſſe</hi> of his <hi>conſcience,</hi> the <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity</hi> of his <hi>conuerſation,</hi> the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>kenes</hi> of his <hi>ſpirit,</hi> the <hi>diſcreetneſſe</hi> of his <hi>behauiour,</hi> &amp; <hi>efficacy</hi> of his <hi>Preaching,</hi> but had rather <hi>feele</hi> their paiment of <hi>gold,</hi> then <hi>heare</hi> their <hi>preaching</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the <hi>gaine</hi> of their <hi>purſes</hi> before the <hi>gaining</hi> of the <hi>ſoules</hi> of their bretheren vnto <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> turning <hi>patronage</hi> into <hi>pillage,</hi> and <hi>truſt</hi> into <hi>tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery,</hi> preſenting <hi>Magus</hi> vnto <hi>Balaam:</hi> ſo that though he be as ſtupid as <hi>Philips</hi> Aſſe in <hi>Plutorch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. Apoth.</note> yet it he be loaden with <hi>gold,</hi> he ſhall be admitted and commended for a man of <hi>gifts;</hi> howſoeuer the old <hi>law</hi> appointed the necke of an <hi>Aſſe</hi> to be broke. <hi>Exo.</hi> 34.<note place="margin">Exod. 34.20.</note> 
               <hi>This</hi> is the reaſon why there are ſo many <hi>Mutes</hi> in this kingdome, and ſo few <hi>vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> in ſome places; ſo many <hi>vowels</hi> which are ſhort in deliuering the Lords preſage: like <hi>Cilchas</hi> in <hi>Homer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>I</hi> liad a.</note> who knew the truth but was afraid to ſpeake it, leaſt hee ſhould anger the hearers and hurt himſelfe; like the flattering <hi>Priest</hi> of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> who when <hi>Alexander</hi> the great came to the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, ſaluted him by the name of <hi>Iupiters</hi> ſonne,<note place="margin">Plut in vit.</note> and all to get ſome great rew ard. So did not S. <hi>Iohn</hi> with <hi>Epheſus,</hi> but <hi>threatneth</hi> a ſpeedy iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without quick <hi>conuerſion. Behold how this concerneth you! Faile</hi> not now in <hi>attention. Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:15635:38"/>is fallen vpon that night wherein <hi>Chriſt</hi> died; <hi>one iudgement</hi> came vpon it,<note place="margin">Applicatio. Zorin. Ac. <hi>18.19.</hi>
               </note> and though it was afterwards <hi>reedified,</hi> yet now it is becom miſerable by <hi>Turkiſh</hi> tyranny and <hi>Greekiſh</hi> ſuperſtition; a poore <hi>Biſhop</hi> and ſome remnants remayning. <hi>God</hi> is the ſame <hi>God</hi> ſtill, as iuſt, as iealous as euer he was. <hi>Our ſinnes being as great as thoſe of Epheſus, nay greater, the like end muſt come vpon vs without repentance.</hi> My <hi>zeale</hi> to Gods glory, and <hi>deſire</hi> for the ſaluations of you all, command me not to flatter. <hi>Remember, London,</hi> from whence thou haſt fallen: Many glorious things haue beene ſpoken of thee, O thou city of God. <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Aegypt</hi> was neuer more happy,<note place="margin">Ammian. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. l. 22.</note> that for many yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſcarce any one day hath beene ſeene, that the Sunne hath not ſhined vpon it.<note place="margin">Platina.</note> But if your <hi>glory</hi> were as great as that of <hi>Rome,</hi> when <hi>Cyneas</hi> the <hi>Epirote</hi> reported that he had ſeene ſo many <hi>Kings</hi> as <hi>Citizens; though</hi> the number of your city hath ſometimes beene found (and now runneth numberleſſe) <hi>aboue eight hundreth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand liuing ſoules; though</hi> you are ſituate among the riuers, hauing the <hi>Sea</hi> for your rampart; <hi>as many learned and religious Teachers to inſtruct you, as euer any one Church ſince the Apoſtles times;</hi> though you haue goodly <hi>houſes</hi> to receiue you, pleaſant <hi>ſhades</hi> to coole you, all <hi>delicats</hi> of Sea and land to feede you:<note place="margin">Plut in Lacon. Theopomp. In hiſt.</note> yet if your <hi>ſtreets</hi> abound with men like the <hi>Graecians,</hi> which knew what was honeſt but did not practiſe it; like <hi>Philips</hi> ſoldiers, who held <hi>periuries, impoſtures, ſhark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:15635:38"/>to be but trickes of a good wit: if you ſuffer many <hi>rorers</hi> to ſweare away all <hi>reproofes,</hi> and drinke away the <hi>chidings</hi> of their own <hi>conſcience:</hi> if you ſuffer <hi>painted Iezabels</hi> to drawe the eyes, and chain the hearts of many vnto them by their <hi>witchcrafts: if</hi> you ſuffer young <hi>Gallants</hi> to be more forward for the <hi>fleſh</hi> then the <hi>Spirit,</hi> being borne to great <hi>poſseſsions,</hi> but like ripe <hi>figtrees</hi> full of fruite growing ouer deepe waters are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the <hi>Iayes,</hi> ſo the <hi>hopes</hi> and meanes of theſe to be blaſted and conſumed by byting <hi>Vſuters, inticing Dalilaes,</hi> and <hi>cozening Cheaters,</hi> till they become <hi>ſports</hi> and <hi>ſubiects</hi> for <hi>Theaters;</hi> if you ſuffer many <hi>conſcience cauterized fooliſh A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts</hi> to ſcoffe at the Goſpell, violently extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing to themſelues the <hi>Sunne-light</hi> of the Scriptures, <hi>Moone-light</hi> of the creature, nay the <hi>ſparkes</hi> and cinders of nature, and to be worſe then the <hi>Diuel,</hi> who belieueth with trembling that there is a God; <hi>If</hi> you ſuffer prophaine <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to weare Gods liuery, and ſerue the Dinell, to be as mutable as <hi>Proteus,</hi> as changeable as the <hi>Camelion,</hi> one day a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> another day a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> reſoluing like <hi>Denton,</hi> in King <hi>Edwards</hi> daies a true <hi>Profeſſour,</hi> but in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> dayes crying, I CANNOT BVRNE, <hi>For which God ſo followed him, that ſhortly after his houſe was fired, &amp; he with two other periſhed in the flame;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fox martir p, <hi>1558.</hi> edi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Anno <hi>1596.</hi>
               </note> nay to turne <hi>Turkes, Iewes, Infidels,</hi> any thing for aduantage. If you ſuffer blood-thirſty <hi>Papiſts,</hi> thoſe vndermining <hi>Foxes,</hi> to haue not onely
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15635:39"/>
               <hi>foueas,</hi> but <hi>fonentes,</hi> their <hi>holes,</hi> but <hi>friends</hi> and <hi>fautors,</hi> and more <hi>Idolatrous</hi> abhominable <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> in ſome <hi>Priſons,</hi> then there are ſermons in ſome <hi>Churches, God muſt come againſt you quickly and remoue his Candleſtick. I remember</hi> that of <hi>Lipſius, Ipſa clementia eſt, in deſparate malos non eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe clementem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lipſ. l. de. vna. rel.</note> It is good clemencie, not to ſhew any clemencie vnto thoſe that are deſperately e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. Suffer therefore the words of exhortation, and let me be your <hi>remembrancer</hi> in theſe things, <hi>elſe I can be no good Miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ti. 4.6.</note> I am now his <hi>Ambaſſadour,</hi> and were I before the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Monarch</hi> of the world, my reſolution ſhould be as that of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Neque Imperiale eſt dicendi libertatem negare.<note place="margin">Amb. ep. l. 5</note>
               </l>
               <l>Neque ſecerdotale quod ſentiat non dicere.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Neither becommeth it you to forbid free ſpeech, neither beſeemeth it me to keepe in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence what I ſhould ſpeake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Right</hi> Honourable <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> of this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and admired Citty,<note place="margin">Sir John Ioules Mayor.</note> who ſit at the ſterne of this common wealth, whoſe <hi>breaſt</hi> is like an <hi>Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> whereinto all the cares of priuate men emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty themſelues, <hi>except</hi> you protect with Gods <hi>ſword</hi> the ſeruice of God, <hi>except</hi> you put to death the <hi>deadly</hi> and crying ſinnes which liue in this Citty, <hi>except</hi> (like thoſe good <hi>ſeruants</hi> of the great King) you ſometimes walke the <hi>ſtreets,</hi> and many idle and irreligious <hi>corners, compelling</hi> the obſtinate, <hi>our Candleſtick must be remoued, God will come againſt you quickly.</hi> You <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſsadours</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:15635:39"/>of the Lord, <hi>Meſsengers</hi> and <hi>Miniſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of my God, <hi>except</hi> you <hi>crye</hi> aloud againſt ſin, <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> the diſeaſed, <hi>heale</hi> that which is ſicke, <hi>bind</hi> vp that which is broken, bring againe that which hath bene driuen away,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z. 34.4.</note> and <hi>ſeeke</hi> that which hath beene loſt; <hi>except</hi> your life and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine agree together, as it was ſpoken of <hi>Origen Quale habuit verbun, talem habuit vitam;</hi> except you paſſe your time as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did,<note place="margin">Hieron Ep. ed Marcel.</note> who ſpent his life either in <hi>reading,</hi> or <hi>meditating,</hi> or <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or <hi>conferring,</hi> or <hi>counſelling,</hi> or <hi>comforting,</hi> or <hi>writing,</hi> or <hi>preaching, Our Candleſtick muſt be remoued, God will come againſt you quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let</hi> me remember you, <hi>aged</hi> and <hi>gray-headed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> whoſe <hi>yeares</hi> haue taught you experience for the world,<note place="margin">1. Io. 2.14.</note> and you profeſſe that you haue knowne God from the beginning, <hi>thinke vppon your latter end.</hi> Let not your <hi>laſt</hi> act bee the <hi>worſt.</hi> For <hi>honourable age,</hi> is not that which ſtandeth in length of time, nor that is meaſured by number of yeares: but <hi>wiſdome</hi> is your <hi>gray-hayre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſd. 4.8.9.</note> and an <hi>vnſpotted</hi> life is your old <hi>age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let</hi> me remember you <hi>young</hi> men and bleſſed <hi>Brethren,</hi> to begin betimes a holy and pure life: <hi>Faint not</hi> at that Prouerb inuented by the <hi>Diuell</hi> that <hi>young Saints proue old Diuels.</hi> Bee <hi>now</hi> trained vp in the way wherein you ſhould goe,<note place="margin">Eraſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>col. piet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s pucril.</note> and when you are old you will not depart from it. I exhort you as <hi>Auſtin, Etiam atque etiam, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pr. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. l. 2. in Ep Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Conſider ye diligently that yee are young men. <hi>Fight</hi> to <hi>ouercome: ouercome</hi> yee to bee <hi>crowned:</hi> Bee hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15635:40"/>minded leaſt yee fall in the fight: <hi>vp</hi> and bee doing, and the Lord ſhall be with you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally</hi> to ſpeake vnto all and ſo to end all: <hi>while</hi> the Lord woeth vs, as hee did <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Iuda,</hi> O <hi>England</hi> what ſhall I doe vnto thee? O <hi>London</hi> how ſhall I entreat thee? Let vs embrace the riches of his mercifull call: <hi>Let</hi> euery one ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that vnto his owne ſoule, which is ſpoken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Angell of the Church in <hi>Sardis: Remember how thou haſt receiued and heard, and hold faſt and repent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Re. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Let</hi> thy <hi>moiſt eyes, furrowed cheekes, hard knees, humble detection, broken ſighs,</hi> teſtifie an humble ſorrow. <hi>Heereafter</hi> let vs neuer looke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Sodome,</hi> but run in a holy race till we come to the gole. <hi>Let</hi> vs caſt anchor in the faire <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> of Gods mercies, the ſafeſt harbour for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Conſciences. <hi>Let</hi> vs commune with our owne <hi>hearts,</hi> and make this one word <hi>Repent</hi> the <hi>watch</hi> of our liues. <hi>Let</hi> vs write this leſſon with the <hi>pen</hi> of a Diamond vpon the <hi>tablet</hi> of our hearts. <hi>Heauen</hi> and our ſoules are vppon this worke, and it ſhould bee our onely labour, for <hi>Tempus vitae eſt tempus poenitentiae,</hi> the whole ſeaſon of our life is but lent vs for mortification. O then while Gods patience expecteth vs, let vs not deferre our repentance; <hi>while</hi> hee importuneth, let not vs ſleep; <hi>while</hi> he knocketh, <hi>let not</hi> vs ſhut the doores of our hearts: but let vs draw nigh vnto God, &amp; hee will draw nigh vnto vs.<note place="margin">Iam. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Let</hi> vs clenſe our hands and purifie our hearts. <hi>Let</hi> vs humble our ſelues in the ſight of the Lord, and hee ſhall lift vs
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15635:40"/>vp: <hi>Hee</hi> ſhall bee our God and wee ſhall bee his People; <hi>Peace,</hi> ſhall bee in your houſes, and plenty in your dwellings; there ſhall bee <hi>no decay,</hi> no leading into captiuity, no <hi>complaining</hi> in your ſtreetes: and which is <hi>better then all theſe,</hi> our <hi>Church</hi> and Candleſtick ſhall neuer be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, till <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> come vnto Iudgement: To whom with the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> bee aſcribed all honour and glory, power and Maieſty, now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
